<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prudential reflections, moral considerations, and stoical maximes In three centuries: written originally in the Spanish tongue, and thence put into French, by a R.F. of the Society. English'd by J. D. of Kidwelly.</title>
            <author>Nieremberg, Juan Eusebio, 1595-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1150B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217842</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829485</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829485</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52344)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1995:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prudential reflections, moral considerations, and stoical maximes In three centuries: written originally in the Spanish tongue, and thence put into French, by a R.F. of the Society. English'd by J. D. of Kidwelly.</title>
                  <author>Nieremberg, Juan Eusebio, 1595-1658.</author>
                  <author>J. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 191, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Ja: Cotterel, for R. Robinson, neer Grays Inne-gate in Holborn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Juan Eusebio Nieremberg.</note>
                  <note>With an initial imprimatur leaf dated Jan. 3. 1673/4.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 59 reads: "Moral considerations"; caption title on p. 125 reads: "Stoical maximes".</note>
                  <note>With an initial imprimatur leaf dated Jan. 3. 1673/4. British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Maxims --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRUDENTIAL REFLECTIONS, MORAL CONSIDERATIONS, And STOICAL MAXIMES.</p>
            <p>IN THREE CENTURIES:</p>
            <p>Written Originally in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue, and thence put into <hi>French,</hi> by a <hi>R. F.</hi> of the <hi>Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Engliſh'd by <hi>J. D.</hi> of <hi>Kidwelly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Ja: Cotterel,</hi> for <hi>R. Robinſon,</hi> neer <hi>Grays</hi> Inne-gate in <hi>Holborn.</hi> 1674.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33925:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33925:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:33925:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> Jan. <hi>3. 1673/4.</hi> Roger L'Eſtrange.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33925:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:33925:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33925:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>PRUDENTIAL REFLECTIONS.</head>
            <p n="1">I. OF all Maſters, Experience is the moſt expert in teaching us to become wiſe and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Nor does it coſt a man much pains to acquire that precious quality, if he does but reflect on the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of others, ſince it is no hard matter for him to learn Wit at their coſt. He who can ſeaſonably make his advantage of <hi>Occaſion,</hi> has attain'd the perfect knowledge of the uſe of things. <hi>That</hi> diſcovers to us the difference there is between a wiſe man, and him who is not ſuch. The former perceives it at a great diſtance, and with conſtancy expects, that he may not let it ſlip; the other ſees it not, as they ſay, but by the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33925:5"/>and when indeed it is quite gone.</p>
            <p n="2">II. THe greateſt art of Prudence does not conſiſt ſo much in minding the preſent, as in well conſidering the future. It is commonly ſaid of a ſort of people, who take upon them to foretel things to come, that their eyes are ſo piercing, as to ſee even through Stone-walls, nay what is under ground: but it is certain, that a man truly-wiſe and prudent, does, with the lights of his mind, diſcover what may be moſt conceal'd in the times yet to come. He never lets ſlip the remembrance of things paſt; he frugally husbands the preſent time, and without any diſquiet provides for the future.</p>
            <p n="3">III. HE who would arrive to the higheſt pitch of Wiſdom and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33925:5"/>Prudence with the aſſiſtance of any Maſter beſides himſelf, muſt always accuſe himſelf, and diligently exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, whether he be not chargeable with the ſame faults which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns in others. A man becomes in a ſhort time Maſter of himſelf, when he makes uſe of other mens imperfections, as an impartial mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to diſcover his own.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. REaſon ought to illuminate all our actions. We ſhould not do that which is good purely out of inclination, nor yet puniſh out of paſſion. Never give order for the chaſtiſing of any one, while you are angry; nor bethink your ſelf of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding, while you are tranſported with joy. Not but that you may conceive a pleaſure in obliging; but it is not any way requiſite, that joy and pleaſure ſhould be the diſtributors of benefits.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33925:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="5">V. NOt to rely too much on Fortune, and always to conſult Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, is a ſecure way for a man to be ſucceſsful in what he undertakes. It argues a greater ability of parts not to prove ſucceſsful with good advice, than for a man to compaſs his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns with temerity.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. SEcrecy is but the key of Prudence. He who communicates his ſecrets to one ſingle perſon, has no reaſon to complain of all the worlds knowing of them: If you are deſirous that a thing ſhould not be known to many, diſcover it not to any one. To little purpoſe does a man confide in his Neighbour, when he betrays himſelf.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. A Fool, while he is ſilent, gains eſteem; and a wiſe man does yet make a ſtronger ſettlement of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33925:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>repute. Men run no hazard, and ſometimes gain much, when they are cautelous and reſerv'd in ſpeaking: but it is ever dangerous, to ſpeak much; and the moſt accompliſh'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the world makes an abatement of his reputation by an over-flux of diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. YOu ſhould never ſay any thing to others, but what you are very well aſſur'd of your ſelf: for if it be a thing wherein a Grandee, or ſome other rich and powerful perſon is concern'd, queſtion not but what you have told another, as a ſecret, will be immediately known. They who make it their work to humour the great and the wealthy, read even the thoughts of other men; and ſo he to whom you have only diſcover'd your ſuſpicion, will be ſure to make paſs for a truth what you haply had not yet throughly imagin'd.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33925:7"/>
            <p n="9">IX. IT is a fortunate fault, nay indeed of very great advantage, to ſpeak commendably of all ſorts of perſons. There is not ſo much reaſon to call thoſe flatterers, who commend not only the rich and the great, but alſo ſpeak well of the abſent, and of ſuch as are in miſery and affliction.</p>
            <p n="10">X. A Man gains the eſteem of all people, when he wiſely governs his Tongue; and he will reap this advantage thereby, that no body will be apt to ſpeak evil of him, who ſpeaks well of all ſorts of perſons.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. THere are ſome perſons, who, out of Prudence, are very deſirous to ſeem well-ſatisfy'd, though they are not really ſo. By that artifice would they ingratiate themſelves
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33925:7"/>with thoſe on whom they have a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, giving their approbation, with a thouſand Elogies, to whatever thoſe perſons cheriſh. Yet after all, a man is no loſer by expreſſing his reſpects for that which another high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteems; and it is leſs dangerous to commend the furniture of a man's Houſe, and the rarities of his Cloſet, than to ſpeak well of his perſon, when there is no occaſion for it.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. A Man accuſes himſelf too haſtily, when he is over-forward to make ſatisfaction. It argues impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in any one to condemn himſelf, while there appears no body againſt him: it is then timely enough to anſwer, and to alledge ones reaſons, when he himſelf is examin'd, and others would be inform'd of the thing in debate. If you conceive the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint which is to be made, to be of ſome importance, Prudence requires
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33925:8"/>that you ſhould prevent the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, and that by the moſt plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excuſes you have, ſatisfie, if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the perſon who thinks himſelf diſoblig'd. But if you are aſſur'd, that there is no cauſe of complaining of you, do not ſo much as think of juſtifying your ſelf; for that were to give greater weight and force to the complaint, which they ſeem deſirous to frame againſt you.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. 'TIs better to receive an injury, than to hear a flattery with pleaſure. Nay, I maintain, that it is not poſſible for one man to outrage another more cruelly, than by beguil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and ſhewing a deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of his judgment. Shut your ears equally againſt flatterers who exceſſively commend, and detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors who relive others without any cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:33925:8"/>
            <p n="14">XIV. WHen a powerful man ſhall ſay any thing to you that is harſh and diſobliging, diſcover not your reſentment thereof, but be perſwaded on the contrary, that he has done you a pleaſure, and that it is a favour you have receiv'd from him. I ſhould ſeem that the words of ſuch perſons have a priviledge, and a particular character, which thoſe of other men have not. Hope not therefore ever to get any ſatisfaction of them. Nay I ſhould not adviſe you to take it, though you might eaſily do ſo. Suffer him therefore to ſpeak freely, in whoſe power it is to make you a partaker of his favours, and of whom you may one time or other ſtand in need.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. THere is nothing more oppoſite to true Prudence, than that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime of State, which directs us to do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33925:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>evil to thoſe of whom we have receiv'd any, ſo to frighten others, and to make them know by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that they ſhall not be more gently treated, if they attack us. Thus is it that a man hides his paſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Veil of Prudence. It is much more eaſie to acquire many friends by meekneſs and an obſervance of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum,</hi> than to preſerve ſome by fear.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. IT is a moſt dangerous thing to be unwilling to pardon. Deſpair makes men attempt ſtrange things. My meaning is, that that perſon has but ſlightly offended you; but if he muſt be your irreconcileable enemy, and that his malice muſt laſt always, he will be in a capacity to injure you much, and in time he will draw in divers others to aſſiſt him in the revenge he intends to take. 'Tis a rare ſight to ſee that man chang'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33925:9"/>whom paſſion had put beſides himſelf, who is not afraid of any thing, and hearkens not either to his friends, or the devoir incumbent on him.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. YOu have no ground at all to complain of the wrong which ſome man has done you, ſince you put your confidence in him, knowing that he had been injurious to others, and had deceiv'd them. You have but too much cauſe to be diſtruſtful of him after that experience; yet do ſo without his perceiving of it.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. FLatter not your ſelf that people ſpeak ſincerely, when they ſay the moſt obliging things in the world of you; if ſuffices that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it when they come to the effects of thoſe ſayings. We finde many perſons who ſpeak no ill of any one, and yet they do no good to any body.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33925:10"/>A man ſhould endeavour to gueſs rightly of the flatteries, which ought to make an experience for the future, and not give them credit but anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably to the effect, wherewith we ſaw them attended at firſt.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. IT is certainly a dangerous thing to offend a man of eminent quality, and one who has an advantage over you; yet is there more danger to have any difference with his real friend; inaſmuch as he thinks his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation wounded, when any one has a pique againſt him, whoſe breaſt he makes the treaſury of all his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets; and therefore it will be a greater trouble to him to forget that injury, than it would be, if he were attack'd in his own perſon. A ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous man is ordinarily ſatisfy'd, when he ſees himſelf in a capacity to chaſtiſe the perſon who had injur'd him; but it is not an eaſie matter for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33925:10"/>him to give a check to his reſentment, when he reflects on the obligation he has to revenge his friend. He may haply conceive, that it argues a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain meanneſs of ſpirit, or at leaſt ſome weakneſs in him, to revenge himſelf; but he thinks that as well his honour as his duty engage him to take ſatisfaction for the affront done his friend.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. IT coſts a man dear to affront a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of high rank. All the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the world, and the moſt real ſervices one can do, will not be able ſometimes to daſh out of his mind the remembrance of the injury he hath receiv'd. No man but looks upon Honour as a thing of right belonging to him, and accordingly muſt have a great averſion for contempt. In fine, it is manifeſt that a man is more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſee himſelf ſleighted, than he is tranſported with joy when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the greateſt honours.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:33925:11"/>
            <p n="21">XXI. THe great Maſter-piece of humane life conſiſts in the ſupporting of the evils that happen. Patience is the moſt ſolid ground-work of Vertue, and men cannot arrive to a real great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, but by extraordinary ſufferings. There is not requir'd ſo much courage to attack a dreadful enemy, as to endure a change of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or ſome other diſaſtrous accident with patience.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. THey who know how to judge impartially, make perfect valour to conſiſt in a ſelf-conqueſt. Kings, who with powerful Armies gain Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and take Cities, are oblig'd for their Lawrels to the gallant perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of their Captains and Soldiers; whereas a true <hi>Heroe,</hi> who has ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd his paſſions, is endebted only to his own valour for that glorious victory.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:33925:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="23">XXIII. A Wicked perſon is capable of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting any one; but it belongs only to a great Soul to ſleight it, and to forbear all diſcovery of the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment thereof. To do evil to others is the eaſieſt thing in the world, but to endure it generouſly and without repining is the hardeſt of any.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. YOu add new ſtrength to your enemy, when you complain of him; nothing contributes more to his ſatisfaction nor renders him more ſcornful and inſolent, than to ſee that you are not able to endure the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief he hath done you. You there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſcover your weakneſs to him, and ſhew him where you are to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd another time: ſo that, to ſpeak properly, you your ſelf are the occaſion of your own trouble. A man takes a pleaſure to ſee a perſon he has
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33925:12"/>oblig'd; but he ever has either a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt or averſion for thoſe whom he hath injur'd.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. IT muſt needs be good for a man to be lov'd by all ſorts of people, but it is dangerous to have any enemy: the truly vertuous are fit for ſociety and converſation. But whereas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is of greater rarity than a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful friend, I adviſe you be extreamly diligent in the ſeeking of him. When you have found him, be aſſur'd your happineſs is not ſmall.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. THere is nothing ſo dangerous as a miſchievous perſon who makes it his ſtudy to conceal his malice: but to little purpoſe does he diſguiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; time will pull off the mask which covers him. Expectation hath its turn after reaſon, and with a little leiſure and patience men diſcover the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33925:12"/>malice and artifices, which ſeem'd to be impenetrable by the moſt illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated minds.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. WHen you have a deſign to ſpeak well of your Friends, do it before all the world: but if to reprove them, it ſhould be in private. He who conſents to the diſorder and tranſgreſſion of his friend, or is ſo meanly-ſpirited as not to divert him from it, becomes himſelf guilty of the ſame fault. The Emperour <hi>Domitian,</hi> who ſeem'd ſent into the world only to do all the miſchief he could in it, has yet left one very rational ſaying behind him, and ſuch as is extreamly conſiderable in the conduct of life: <hi>The ſilence of good people gives a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to evil ſpeakers; and it is an augmentation of their fury, for a man not to trouble himſelf in checking the courſe of their malevolence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33925:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. WE cannot ſpeak of riches but according to the good or bad uſe which is made of them. Money is a ſlave when a man knows how to employ it ſeaſonably; and it becomes Maſter of him who over-minds the getting of it, or uſes it not as he ought. You make great purchaſes, when you relieve thoſe that are in neceſſity. A merciful man gains more by doing good, than thoſe very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on whom his bounties are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. IF it happen that one asks any thing of you, be not tedious in anſwering him. A man is but half-deceiv'd when he has a ſudden and peremptory denyal.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33925:13"/>
            <p n="30">XXX. A Denyal is a kinde of heart<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>breaking to ſuch as are deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably poor, and have no way to help themſelves; but there is no evil more hardly ſupportable than ingratitude.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. THere is a great reſemblance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a liberal perſon, and him who ſows in the field. The Labourer caſts his grain at random; the winde carries ſome away and ſhuffles it as it liſts; the Birds devour ſome part of it, which is conſequently turn'd into ordure: but the other part which chanc'd to fall deep enough into the ground, after it has continu'd there a while, as it were interr'd, will by its appearance glad the Labourer's fight, and return into his Barn with intereſt.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33925:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="32">XXXII. DO all the good you can while you are in favour with Fortune, and you will find the effects of it in the time of adverſity. He to whom you have done any good, when he expected it not, thinks himſelf doubly oblig'd. All the world is beholding to him who is kinde to the good.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. HE who gives no body any thing is Treaſurer to his Heir; who, after the death of that Miſer, will conceal the real joy of his Soul, under feigned tears and a perſonated grief. The avarice of old men is a very ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary monſter in the world; but to ſpeak exactly of the earneſtneſs of rich perſons to augment their reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, methinks it may be ſaid, that that very deſire and paſſion is nothing elſe, but a kinde of poverty very richly furniſh'd.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33925:14"/>
            <p n="34">XXXIV. DEny not that to others which happly you will be oblig'd in your turn to ask of them; and if you are wiſe, ask not that which you have deny'd. Do juſtice to him who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires it of you, and do thoſe a kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whom you ſhall think worthy of it.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. NOthing is more eaſily blotted out than a good turn; it is a loſs of it, if a man do but remember it, or repent himſelf that he had done it. It argues an extream imprudence, for one to regret the good he has done; for by that means he twice loſes the thing he has given: It is no longer his, when another hath receiv'd it; and the gift is loſt again, when a man thinks too much upon it.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:33925:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. IT is ever more advantageous to give, than to receive. When you do good to others, you engage them into your intereſts, and you ſeem to aſſume to your ſelf a ſupremacy over them; whereas if you receive any thing of them, you become in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner their Slave. Brag not of having oblig'd your Friend; 'tis an injury to him, if you do but ſpeak of it. Leave it to him to celebrate your generoſity; you cannot deſire a more remarkable teſtimony of his gratitude.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. THere is no great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an ungrateful perſon, and him who complains too openly that he was deny'd the favour he hoped for. He is much to blame to call that injuſtice, which at moſt amounts but to a defect of liberality; a man who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>means himſelf ſo, not diſtinguiſhing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33925:15"/>what is due upon the ſcore of juſtice from that which is granted out of liberality, never thinks himſelf oblig'd to gratitude.</p>
            <p n="38">XXXVIII. A Man is not oblig'd to give al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, when he has given often; nay, it ſeems he ſhould have the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to deny ſometimes, eſpecially when he has loſt his benefits by obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ungrateful perſons: but it is out of all doubt, that he who is a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual receiver, has not upon that ſcore ever the more right to ask.</p>
            <p n="39">XXXIX. INgratitude is a very common thing amongſt men. It ſeldom happens that the remembrance of a good turn laſts longer than a day. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a benefit is eaſily blotted out by the greatneſs of an injury; and there is ſo much corruption amongſt men, that they think not themſelves
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33925:16"/>oblig'd to celebrate any commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the favours they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, when they are once offended.</p>
            <p n="40">XL. SUffer not your ſelf to be dazzled with the favour of great perſons, and, if you will take my advice, never rely too much on their friendſhip. A man cannot fly very high with bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd wings. Nothing more uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant than Fortune; ſhe many times caſts thoſe down the precipice, whom ſhe had had the pleaſure to exalt: but though that ſhould not happen, yet let this be your perſwaſion, that men have not alwayes the ſame incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
            <p n="41">XLI. WHen you are admitted into the ſhade of ſome powerful perſon's proſperity and advancement, work not out your own ruine, by procuring that of others; but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33925:16"/>that every day the Sun ſets and diſappears. It argues ſimplicity in a man, to think to be the Friend of one ſingle perſon, only that he may injure and prejudice all others.</p>
            <p n="42">XLII. IF you are in favour with your Prince, employ your credit and intereſt to oblige as many people as you can, and make not your advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his countenance to injure any one. Endeavour ſo prudently to hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band your good fortune, as that all your Friends may be oblig'd to look on it as their own. In fine, give all perſons occaſion to congratulate your being ſo highly in favour with him who can do all things.</p>
            <p n="43">XLIII. MAke not an open profeſſion of your being a Favourite, if it be not already known to all people; diſſemble it for a time, and content
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33925:17"/>your ſelf with a ſecret ſatisfaction of your own happineſs, till ſuch time as it becomes publick, and be known generally, to both Grandees and thoſe of the meaner ſort: and then you may freely own it, and make the leſs difficulty to ſollicit on their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, who ſhall deſire it of you, even though they are not likely to obtain what they engage you to deſire for them. The very inclination you ſhall assure them of that you have to oblige them, will no doubt abundantly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie them; and if it happen that the affair which you have recommended does not ſucceed according to their expectation, they cannot complain of any but him, on whom it abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely depend.</p>
            <p n="44">XLIV. YOu never raiſe a Structure well when you do it too haſtily What is done with precipitation eaſily falls, as being not well ſupported
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33925:17"/>Be not ſo fond as to imagine, that you can raiſe your ſelf all of a ſudden, though you think your ſelf to be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in favour, for fear of a ſudden pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitation into diſgrace.</p>
            <p n="45">XLV. LEvel your pretenſions to a mean Fortune, ſince of all the different conditions of men, this is the moſt happy and moſt deſirable; a man lives in it with more tranquillity, and is leſs expos'd to danger than in any of the reſt. A high pitch of Fortune is attended with a thouſand vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and every thing is to be fear'd in that ſtation. Exceſs of wealth o'rwhelms a man, and brings him into danger every minute. The thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt more commonly reduces the loftieſt houſes into aſhes, than the poor Cottages of Shepherds: and the firſt fit of ſickneſs ordinarily brings down the ſtrongeſt and moſt robuſt bodies.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:33925:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="46">XLIV. OF all the paſſions, Hope is that which is likely to do us moſt prejudice; I mean that which relyes only on the favour of men. This ordinarily deceives us, and after it has inſpir'd thoſe who are cajol'd by it, with ſome great deſigns, it precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates them into a dreadful abyſſe of misfortunes.</p>
            <p n="47">XLVII. BE ever diſtruſtful of a fearful and cowardly perſon, as being the more to be fear'd than others, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that, wanting audacity and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, he will be apt to make uſe of Artifices and treachery. You will finde it leſs trouble to make your party good againſt two open Enemies, than againſt one only, when he diſguiſes and conceals himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33925:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. PErfidious and fearful men are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily of weak Intellectuals, extreamly diſtruſtful, credulous in the higheſt degree, cruel, and ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. Fear, which makes them ſee danger where there is not any, does withal perſwade them, that it ſhould be prevented; and thence it comes that they are in perpetual diſtruſt; and though the ambuſhes they are afraid of are purely imaginary, yet ſince it is their abſolute perſwaſion, that they are really ſo, they look upon moſt people as their enemies, though moſt commonly others do not ſo much as think of them. From this kinde of fear proceeds hatred, and this latter begets that deſire of revenge which nothing can check. Nay, ſometimes they are hurried on to exceſſes that are barbarous and full of cruelty, wherein the moſt innocent are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd: no artifice which they will
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33925:19"/>not make uſe of, to deſtroy thoſe whom they think to be their enemies; and they are never ſecure and undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd, till they have remov'd out of their way whatever is the occaſion of their fear. So that it may be ſaid of cowardly and perfidious perſons, that they are Prodigal, ſince they ſo dearly purchaſe not valour, but repoſe and tranquillity.</p>
            <p n="49">XLIX. TO the former reflection this may be added, that there is ſome ground to dread a perſon who is himſelf afraid of falling into extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary neceſſity, inaſmuch as avarice ever inſpires a man with criminal and barbarous ſentiments. Treachery and perfidouſneſs, clubbing with cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, ſupplies the defect of valour; ſo that a man who has no generoſity is more to be fear'd than he that has much. But from him who knows not what to do, and dreads miſery
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33925:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and poverty, a man ought to expect nothing but horrid cruelties, and a procedure abſolutely barbarous.</p>
            <p n="50">L. WHen a man hopes for nothing, he fears nothing. It is a difficult matter to deveſt that man of fear, who indifferently fears all things, who grows pale and trembles upon the leaſt occaſion: But when he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects to fortifie himſelf againſt thoſe falſe alarms, and ſuffers himſelf to be o'repreſs'd with the weight which ſeems to be faſten'd to that ſort of fear, it may be concluded that the evil is paſt all remedy.</p>
            <p n="51">LI. IF you conſider that you are a man, your misfortunes will not ſeem new to you; and if you reflect on the diſgraces which happen to others, I am confident your own will ſeem light to you.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33925:20"/>
            <p n="52">LII. TAke things always by the beſt handle: many who think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unfortunate, are ſuch only ſo far as they compare themſelves with thoſe that are more fortunate. The misfortune which is common, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a ſubject of conſolation, or at leaſt alleviates much of the affliction. And experience makes it ſufficiently manifeſt, that an ordinary diſgrace ceaſes to be ſo; nay does not retain ſo much as the name, when it is counter-balanc'd with a greater.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. TIs not well done for a man to hunt on another's Lands; but, in my judgment, it is a much greater fault, for any one to ſeek his diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement and ſatisfaction only in thoſe places where he is not himſelf concern'd. It is requiſite the heart ſhould entertain it ſelf with its proper
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33925:20"/>good; nothing is more likely to finde it matter of gladneſs, than a good diſpoſition of body and minde. A man who is in perfect health, and hungry, is content with the moſt ordinary refreſhments, and finds them very good.</p>
            <p n="54">LIV. SObriety excites the appetite, and gives meats a better guſto. A criminal pleaſure leaves only vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and bitterneſs behind it; whereas a ſatisfaction which is not contrary to vertue, fills the Soul with a certain ſweetneſs, which continues in it a long time. The moſt intolerable afflictions are alleviated by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p n="55">LV. AN enemy is always to be fear'd, how deſpicable ſoever he ſeems to be. There's none more ready to do an ill turn, than they who have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33925:21"/>not either honour or courage. A man never wants reaſons, when he would deny any thing, or is reſolv'd to do miſchief to others. A danger ſlighted will not be long ere it returns.</p>
            <p n="56">LVI. THere is much to be gotten in the company of perſons of good repute; but, on the contrary, there's nothing more dangerous than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with the debauch'd. The beſt-grounded vertue is always apt to rotter in their company, at leaſt it ſuffers an abatement of its eſteem, and has much ado to keep its luſtre. Good advice contributes exceedingly, and good example is of great force to perſwade; and we ſee there needs only that to inſpire the moſt meanly-ſpirited with fervour and generous reſolutions. Among good people a man meets with theſe two advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: Their example animates us, and the advices we receive from them put
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33925:21"/>all our actions into order. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is to be ſaid of the vicious: Their counſels involve ſuch as follow them in great misfortunes, and their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample induces the moſt reſerv'd to renounce all modeſty. It happens or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, that among wicked men, a vertuous man is in a manner vex'd to be ſuch.</p>
            <p n="57">LVII. Diſſimulation buries many inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and checks the current of many affronts, which men would hardly avoid without it. 'Tis not to be imagin'd, that he, who does us an affront, out of the malice he hath conceiv'd againſt us, is the only cauſe of it; but that we alſo contribute thereto, when we do not patiently endure it.</p>
            <p n="58">LVIII. THe moſt innocent and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceptible of all revenges, is,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33925:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>not to make any ſhow of having been offended; in regard the vexation and diſpleaſure which our enemy pretended to give us, when he did us the affront, recoils upon him, and extreamly torments him, ſeeing us not mov'd ſo much at it as he had imagin'd to himſelf: So that he is enrag'd to finde himſelf fruſtrated of his expectation, and ſo ſuffers the puniſhment of his ill will.</p>
            <p n="59">LIX. A Man ſhould never trouble his thoughts with the events of things, at leaſt not diſcover diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, when they happen not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his deſires. If any diſgrace befal you, diſcover not your grief thereat, that ſo you may mortifie your enemy. If on the contrary things ſucceed well, to your deſire, moderate your joy, that you may ſerve for an example to the ambitious.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33925:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="60">LX. A Caſtle is attack'd at that part of it which is, weakeſh. It is imprudence in us, to diſcover where our minds are moſt expos'd to aſſault, and can make leaſt reſiſtance; it will not be long ere the enemy ſtorm us at that very place. Demean your ſelf therefore ſo, as that it may not be known what you are moſt ſenſibly mov'd at.</p>
            <p n="61">LXI. A Man eaſily becomes Maſter of another's heart, when he ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies his inclinations; and he enters into it, as they ſay, at the breach, when he makes uſe of that innocent artifice, to inſinuate into his favour. It is not ſo eaſie a matter , as 'tis imagin'd, to pleaſe people; to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs it well, there muſt be an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of dexterity and good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, eſpecially when a man would not do it by flattery.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:33925:23"/>
            <p n="62">LXII. BE ſlow and conſiderate in the undertaking of any affair, and expeditious in the execution of it. To put an honourable period to a War in a ſhort time, a man muſt reflect on many things: there is already a great progreſs made in a work, when, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is begun, a man has taken all the leiſure requiſite to think on it.</p>
            <p n="63">LXIII. HE ſhews himſelf an entravagant perſon, who runs the hazard of loſing his reputation, out of an exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive earneſtneſs to preſerve it. This ordinarily happens to him, who, to maintain it, uſes too many words. For if it be paſſion that ſuggeſts them to him, though he have reaſon of his ſide, yet will he exceed his limits, and be chargeable with ſome exceſs. So that he will more prejudice himſelf,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33925:23"/>by the manner of vindicating his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, than his enemy could have done, by endeavouring to deprive him of it unjuſtly.</p>
            <p n="64">LXIV. ENvy corrupts Fortune, as the worm gnaws and ſpoils timber. Not, to ſay truth, but that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways better to be the envy'd, than the envious, ſince the latter cannot avoid the infamy which is inſeparable from that vice; whereas the other finds himſelf in an honourable ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, wherein there is glory to be acquir'd.</p>
            <p n="65">LXV. ONe man cannot have a more dreadful enemy than another man; and if envy hath inſtill'd its venom into the heart of that enemy, there is no antidote ſtrong enough to prevent the effect of it. Jealouſie it ſelf cauſes more diſorders, and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33925:24"/>more enmities, than all the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages which a man can receive from the moſt irreconcileable enemies. Envy is never found in that exact meaſure which we call mediocrity; it is always extreamly pernicious, unleſs it be when it has vertue for its object; for then it is moſt excellent.</p>
            <p n="66">LXVI. THere's but little credit to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to what a paſſionate man ſayes: he whom we know to be truly diſ-intereſs'd, deſerves more to be credited; but the envious perſon, not at all.</p>
            <p n="67">LXVII. AN unlawful gain, and ſuch as comes not by direct wayes, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions more damage, than real loſſes do, which way ſoever they happen: a man is ſenſibly mov'd at theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but once, but the remembrance of the former will never out of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33925:24"/>minde, but prove a perpetual ſource of diſcontents.</p>
            <p n="68">LXVIII. NEver account that a gain which makes an addition to your wealth, but only that which brings you ſome luſtre and repute; have therefore a greater eſteem of the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of your good name, of than of that of your riches. A man who grows rich at the coſt of his honour, loſes more than he imagines. A noble reputation is a great inheritance.</p>
            <p n="69">LXIX. THere is no ſafety in the world; the wicked perſon fears the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Laws; the juſt perſon has occaſion to fear the humorouſneſs and inconſtancy of fortune. A man is always more confident, when he hath a long time ruminated upon what he ought to do.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:33925:25"/>
            <p n="70">LXX. MEn get ſooner and more eaſily out of the dangers whereto they are expos'd in this world, by wiſe counſels, than by great ſtrength. 'Tis a greater evil not to know how to live well, than not to be able to live at all. It is much more hard to give a check to Fortune, than to meet her.</p>
            <p n="71">LXXI. KEep your word, and be exact in the performance of all your promiſes; a man has nothing to loſe when he has loſt his credit, and paſſes for a perſon uncapable of any truſt. There are ſome ſo accuſtom'd to ſwear, that men hardly believe them, when they ſpeak moſt truly. He who takes no pleaſure in hearing the truth, will be backward enough to ſpeak it. Flattery is an extreamly-dangerous evil, yet ſuch as will ſtill have its courſe.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33925:25"/>
            <p n="72">LXXII. TO credit all that is ſaid, and not to credit any thing, are two extremities that ought to be avoided; the former is an exceſs of good nature or complaiſance, but there's more ſafety in the other.</p>
            <p n="73">LXXIII. IT is manifeſt, that a man is no great Lover of the truth, when he does what he condemns in others. 'Tis a deceit much of the ſame ſtamp, for a man not to do what he ſays; but it is a ſelf-deceit in him, not to ſpeak as he thinks.</p>
            <p n="74">LXXIV. WHat miſchief ſoever another has done you, yet ought you not ever to ſleight or hate him; 'twere madneſs for a man to be apt to ſin, upon the ſcore of the hatred he bears to the ſinner. You would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33925:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>a man void of judgment, if you ſhould be unwilling to preſerve your innocence, becauſe another has loſt his. You muſt not chaſtiſe one ſin by another.</p>
            <p n="75">LXXV. IF you be not abſolutely a vertuous perſon, have at leaſt ſome kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for thoſe who are like you; if you have ceas'd to be wicked, be not ſo ready to condemn thoſe who are yet ſuch, and allow them a little time to take a ſurvey of themſelves.</p>
            <p n="76">LXXVI. VVHen a man judges with precipitation, it is not long ere he repents of it. As it is in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner impoſſible to give a very exact account of a perſon, whom one had ſeen only running; ſo can we not rightly judge of a thing, which we had but very ſuperficially examin'd.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:33925:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="77">LXXVII. LIve in peace with all men; be always in hoſtility againſt vices, and in perfect harmony with your ſelf. To compaſs this, you are only to make a conſonancy between your words and thoughts, your actions and words, and your deſires and actions.</p>
            <p n="78">LXXVIII. SInce it is impoſſible things ſhould always ſucceed as we would have them, 'tis fit our inclination ſhould comply with the event, whatever it be. A man is eas'd of abundance of cares and diſtractions, when he can well regulate his deſires. 'Tis impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for a man over-earneſtly to wiſh for that which he has not within his power, or what is yet at a great diſtance from him, and to neglect the preſent, which is within his reach.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:33925:27"/>
            <p n="79">LXXIX. FOr a man to accommodate himſelf to the time, is a very noble Science; nay, ſuch as is not unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a King. I account you the moſt unfortunate of all ſlaves, if you ſerve by force and againſt your inclination; whereas if you ſerve willingly and cheerfully, you nobly ſet off your ſervitude.</p>
            <p n="80">LXXX. A Man ſhould ſtand more in fear of his Conſcience than of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon report. The happineſs of the happieſt perſons conſiſts in leading a pure and innocent life. The greateſt commendation a man can have, is, that he deſerves it. It ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for a man to ſeem to be what he is not; but it concerns him above all things, really to be ſuch as he ought to be. What advantage will it be to you to receive a thouſand
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33925:27"/>Elogies from others, if your own Conſcience tells you that you do not deſerve them?</p>
            <p n="81">LXXXI. I Extreamly ſuſpect magnificent promiſes; there is ſome ground to think, that he who makes them would laugh at others, or that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages himſelf to little purpoſe. Things that are rare and very extraordinary ought rather to be given than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd. Do great things, and promiſe them not.</p>
            <p n="82">LXXXII. A Man doubles his gift, when he gives ſpeedily. The Will is that which is moſt precious in the preſents that are made; and that is yet much more remarkable, when a man makes haſt to offer what he is able to do. It is requiſite that good offices ſhould ſurpaſs injuries, and that acknowledgements ſhould always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed benefits.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:33925:28"/>
            <p n="83">LXXXIII. TIs a happineſs for a man, that he can be reprov'd when he does amiſs the moſt happy in this world have it not; and <hi>Iſocrates</hi> affirms, that it is not to be found in the Courts of Princes. Perſons of mean condition have not, as they, ſo many enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of life, as not minding delights provided they have wherewithal to live; but they have this advantage, that ſome are not afraid to admoniſh them, when they do not what they ought; beſides that the Laws are a bridle to them. Princes are depriv'd of that benefit, for they converſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly but with very few perſons, and thoſe make it their only buſineſs to humour them.</p>
            <p n="84">LXXXIV. HE who is appointed to command others, ought to have the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Father, and not the ſeverity
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33925:28"/>of a Maſter. No ſupremacy but is unpleaſant; they who are ſubject thereto finde it always heavy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable; and therefore it ſhould be made as gentle as may be, and no command iſſued out, but what is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd with much meekneſs.</p>
            <p n="85">LXXXV. BE willing to hear all people, and afterwards do what you ſhall think moſt convenient. Never commit the execution of your deſign to him who had been unwilling to approve it. 'Tis a ſhame to fail twice in the ſame thing, ſince we ſee animals ſtop at the firſt and ſtand on their guards, that they may not fall a ſecond time.</p>
            <p n="86">LXXXVI. BE always miſtruſtful of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which is conſonant to your own deſire, and fear the iſſue of it. You will be thought a perſon of no
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33925:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>great judgment, if you proſecute what you have ill begun; and people will have occaſion to call you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, if you quit your enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</p>
            <p n="87">LXXXVII. OF all the counſels which may be follow'd, the ſafeſt is the beſt; the readieſt, that which is moſt ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; the moſt pleaſing, that which is moſt eaſie the moſt advantageous, that which comprehends all theſe. <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> had reaſon to ſay what the admirable <hi>Celſius</hi> relates of him, commending his reflection; <hi>That the ſoveraign perfection of a Phyſician con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in curing his Patient ſafely, in a ſhort time, and delightfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="88">LXXXVIII. BE not too much wedded to you own ſentiments. If you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them with obſtinacy, moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, meerly to comply with you
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33925:29"/>humour, and to avoid offending you, will leave you in errour, and be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of reproving you.</p>
            <p n="89">LXXXIX. THe famous Law-giver <hi>Solon</hi> would not have a man ſtand Neuter in the diviſion of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: and yet when two perſons of great Authority have a difference, and are in hoſtility one againſt the other, it is not, methinks, too ſafe for one to declare himſelf for either party. For thoſe two men coming afterwards to be reconcil'd, as it or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily happens, he will be at the greateſt loſs in the world; in regard the one will be apt to forget the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he had done him, and the other will ever remember the affront which he conceives to have been done him by one who had deſerted his intereſts. Yet is it to be obſerv'd, that they who take no ſide in a popular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, are like the Bats, who are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33925:30"/>peck'd at by the Birds, and bitten by the Mice; ſuch people being in great danger, as having not dar'd to hazard any thing. Not but that there may be much danger for one to endeavour to diſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>engage himſelf from danger. The affliction of a juſt perſon is an evil accompany'd with happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. What favour ſoever men may receive of fortune, yet can they not forbear complaining of her.</p>
            <p n="90">XC. CRuelty is an ordinary companion of ſenſuality; and it may be ſaid of him who is immers'd in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that he is a ſlave to his paſſions, that he lives like a beaſt, and that he hardly has any thing of a man.</p>
            <p n="91">XCI. VVE cannot give a better defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the modiſhneſs and magnificence of apparel, than by calling it, the Superſcription of vanity
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33925:30"/>and pride. It is an argument of little judgment, for a man to be very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſive, to gain the reputation of a vain and ambitious perſon, and to impoveriſh himſelf, purpoſely to get the repute of being rich.</p>
            <p n="92">XCII. AMbition is ſubject two great indiſpoſitions; it is always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly odious, and at the end of it is ordinarily very fatal. It is ſeldom ſeen that that man proſpers, who is ſo temerarious, as to think to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance himſelf above his Maſter.</p>
            <p n="93">XCIII. THings remarkable for their ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſingularity bring not any profit to thoſe that are poſſeſs'd of them; and it is a hard matter to preſerve long that which pleaſes all people.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33925:31"/>
            <p n="94">XCIV. THe revolutions and deſtructions of Empires are not ſo much to be attributed to the multitude of crimes, as to their impunity. We can expect nothing but a dreadful confuſion of all things, when it is lawful to do any thing, and Juſtice it ſelf is ſleighted. In fine, the evil is paſt all remedy, when the Judges and Magiſtrates, inſtead of ſeverely puniſhing the guilty, become them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves complices in their crimes.</p>
            <p n="95">XCV. THere is leſs danger in being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſevere, than in being exceſſively indulgent; and a highly rigorous treatment of men is not ſo prejudicial to the State, as the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing of abſolute freedom and licentiouſneſs. If the Judges are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs and negligent in the puniſhing of crimes, God will infallibly lift up his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33925:31"/>hand to chaſtiſe both People and Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together. The juſt perſon is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly injur'd, when the guilty are pardon'd. Nothing approaches nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the perfection of juſtice, than ſeverity.</p>
            <p n="96">XCVI. THe ſtrongeſt protection of a Monarchy, and the beſt caution the people can have for their ſecurity, is, that Prince and People ſubmit to all the Laws, and have a reſpect for the commands, which God hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd for the obſervance of them. The ſlighting of Magiſtrates, and thoſe who are entruſted with the Government, proves ever fatal to the Republick: when people have loſt the reſpect due to them, they are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily induc'd to make no account of the Laws.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:33925:32"/>
            <p n="97">XCVII. WHen in any Government they only are advanc'd to publick charges who are moſt rich, and proffer the greateſt bribe for them, it cannot ſubſiſt long. Thoſe very perſons will make no difficulty to embroyl it again for Money. If there be a kinde of Traffick and Commerce in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of charges and honourable em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, perſons of merit will for the moſt part be excluded, and the rich only-will be advanc'd thereto; ſo that to get more wealth, they will learn to commit a thouſand unjuſt actions; and when after wards they ſhall grow expert in that dangerous Science, and have the power in their own hands, they will inſolently ſleight all the obligations of juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33925:32"/>
            <p n="98">XCVIII. THe vulgar knows not wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the mean ſignifies, but always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines to one of the two extremities when they ſleight a thing, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways degrade it lower than it ought to be; when they commend it, 'tis with an inſupportable exceſs.</p>
            <p n="99">XCIX. THough there be nothing more unconſtant than the affection of the people, yet muſt it be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd withal, that there is not any thing ſo powerful; for we always finde, that the greater number car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it; and, to tell things as they are, moſt people take that ſide. It is a rare thing to meet with a man who is willing to hearken to reaſon, when in a manner all reject it. Who can oppoſe the multitude? 'Tis a River overflown, violently carrying along with it whatever reſiſts its current.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33925:33"/>When the populacy acts without paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it may be ſaid, that its voice is the voice of God; when it is hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by paſſion, 'tis the voice of the Devil. There are but few whom paſſion does not ſometimes force to exceed the limits of reaſon; but it is yet more extraordinary, to finde a man ſo regular and circumſpect in all his actions, as never to make one ſtep awry.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33925:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>MORAL CONSIDERATIONS.</head>
            <p n="1">I. THe deſign of our Creation was to be happy; and yet we are ſo unhappy, as not to know our happineſs; or if we do know it, we do not ſufficiently eſteem it. How would you have a man take the right way, when he is ignorant of the place whither he is to go? Felicity is a good that is peculiar to us, and they are deceiv'd who look on it as an accidental one, whereto we have no right. There are ſome people whoſe conduct is very irregular; for having in their own houſes whatever is requiſite, in order to a contented and happy life in this world, they do not ſo much as reflect on it, but take great Journeys, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33925:34"/>put themſelves to incredible inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, to ſeek for that which they have at home.</p>
            <p n="2">II. I Would not have men make any difference between that happineſs, which is perfect and ſolid, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; and yet if any one will ſtand ſo far upon it, as to maintain they are not one and the ſame thing, he will not however deny, that the one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſiſt without the other. He will be forc'd at leaſt to acknowledge, that vertue is as 'twere the inſtrument of that felicity, which we may enjoy during the courſe of this mortal life. It cannot be deny'd, but that felicity is a good. Now what greater good is there, than that of being vertuous? If it be juſt and rational for a man to deſire the things which all the world eſteems good and advantagious, will it not alſo be ſo for him, to uſe the utmoſt of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33925:34"/>to become a good and vertuous man?</p>
            <p n="3">III. VErtue is of that excellency and value in it ſelf, that it would not have any advantages beſides thoſe whereof it is poſſeſs'd. It has ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently wherewithall to ſatisfie it ſelf for all the pains and inconveniences it endures: the worthieſt and higheſt recompence of a noble action, is the glory of having done it. Goodneſs has certain charms ſo inſinuating and ſo obliging, that the moſt vicious cannot forbear loving it. And indeed we finde, that in their greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, they adore its Image, though it has not a line but what is counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit; for if we take their words, they ſeek after good, and what ſeems beſt to them.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:33925:35"/>
            <p n="4">IV. GOod hath always this advantage, that, being made for it ſelf, it loſes nothing of its goodneſs. Evil, on the contrary, does not change its nature, though it be done in order to a greater good; and there is no abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of its malice, even when a man is inclin'd thereto, as to the thing which ſeems to be beſt, and moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous.</p>
            <p n="5">V. IT is no hard matter to counterfeit vertue; vice ordinarily borrows its name, its attractions, and all its externals. In a word, 'tis not the action, but the intention, which makes the difference between both.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. IT cannot be deny'd, but that Vertue implies much grandeur, ſince it is vertue, to ſpeak properly, that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33925:35"/>makes Grandees; and it was ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaid by <hi>Zeno,</hi> that a man who is great and advanc'd in the world, does not immediately upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count become vertuous, but from the moment of his being vertuous, he is great, according to the true notion of Grandeur. Howe'r it may happen, fortune will ever be forc'd to give place to vertue. A man ceaſes not to live, when he dies in the defence of vertue.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. VErtue raiſes a man much above himſelf; vice degrades him, and renders him leſs than man. It is not only out of an obſervance of decorum, that we love Vertue, but there is alſo a neceſſity obliging us to do it, if we are deſirous to ſecure to our ſelves the advantages which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath given us. He who thinks he has reaſon to ſtand aloof from that raviſhing light, is not only irrational,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33925:36"/>but alſo degrades himſelf into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition below that of beaſts.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. NEver call any thing by the name of Good, but what is able to render men good and vertuous. Though all the world ſhould be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to render you the greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, though you were poſſeſs'd of all the riches upon earth, though your health were perfect and unalterable; yet can it not be ſaid that you are good, if in very deed you have not vertue. It matters not much that all things be wanting to you , if you have but vertue; and ſince you cannot be depriv'd of the quality of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous man, that quality, of all thoſe which may be poſſeſs'd in this world, is the moſt noble, the moſt glorious, and the moſt excellent.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:33925:36"/>
            <p n="9">IX. THere is nothing but deceitfulneſs in riches, honours vaniſh, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune commonly precipitates thoſe who had been her greateſt darlings. Look not therefore on that as a good which may cauſe ſo much evil, and cannot render you ever the better man. Vertue injures no man, it is beneficial to all; and though it go alone, yet is it to be preferred before all the reſt put together.</p>
            <p n="10">X. THe moſt ſharp-ſighted amongſt the Philoſophers were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that Good could not be exactly defin'd, otherwiſe than by affirming it to be a ſource admirably pure, out of which men draw a Million of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages. To add ſomewhat to that conception, we may call it a moſt precious chanel, which hath vertue for its ſource, or which brings it down
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33925:37"/>to us. Without vertue no man can be happy in this life, and it is vertue alſo that makes us happy after our death: it is not only beneficial to the ſoul, but alſo extreamly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to the body, contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to our well being, both in this life and the other.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. KEep at the greateſt diſtance you can from vice, and imitate not thoſe low-ſpirited perſons, who are ſo often obſerv'd to ſay, <hi>In troth 'tis all I was able to do, my ſtrength would not permit me to go any farther.</hi> 'Twere as good to ſay, <hi>I can, but I will not acquire vertue;</hi> when a man, as ſome ordinarily do, makes this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>I would with all my heart, but it is not in my power to avoid that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, nor reform my ſelf of this or that Vice.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:33925:37"/>
            <p n="12">XII. THe earth is at as great a diſtance from the Heavens, as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are from the earth; there is an equal diſtance from the one of thoſe extremities to the other, and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obſerve any inequality but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween vertue and vices. True it is, 'tis a much ſhorter cut to get from vertue to vice, than from vice to vertue.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. VErtue being the nobleſt and moſt advantageous of all qualities, it is but juſt ſhe ſhould have the moſt honourable ſtation; and thence it comes, that we finde her always in the middle: 'tis the work of Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to aſſign her her place, and that does ſo adjuſt things, that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have too much, nor yet want ought requiſite for their perfection.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:33925:38"/>
            <p n="14">XIV. VIce is always lodg'd near Vertue, and therefore 'tis no wonder, that, many times, men ſeeking the latter ſhould meet with the former. Stand therefore on your guard, that you be not deceiv'd. It is further to be obſerv'd, that there are men <hi>in effigie,</hi> and real men; that is, to ſpeak without riddle, there are ſolid vertues, and others that have only the appearance of ſuch. Vertue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd is a ſtrange Monſter. Know, that an action good of it ſelf, done without diſcretion, and with an evil intention, has only the bark and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of vertue; but it has indeed all the deformity of vice.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. NOr would I have you content your ſelf with the vertues which are really ſuch, in regard that among thoſe, there are ſome, called
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33925:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſimple, others ſolid. The former, indeed, are extreamly weak, and of ſhort continuance; the others are ſtrong, and reſiſt any thing. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, a little Lyon is as much a Lyon as a great one, yet there is a great difference between them. A ſtrong and heroick vertue is always attended by ſeveral other vertues; a weak vertue is indeed a vertue, but in regard of its weakneſs, it has not a retinue of other vertues.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. MAke uſe of reaſon, as Lyons do of their Claws, Harts of their Feet, and Herons of their Wings; to preſerve their lives, and to defend themſelves againſt thoſe who attack them. There is no ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſo ſmall and deſpicable, but Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſupply'd it with ſome Arms for its defence; but endowing man with reaſon, ſhe hath made a greater account of him, and more ſenſibly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33925:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>oblig'd him, than all the reſt of the creatures put together.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. A Lyon would not live long with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his offenſives, which are his fore-feet; a Wilde Boar, that ſhould have his Tusks ſtruck or fil'd off, would not be able to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf long. So a man who does not act by the dictamen of reaſon can make no great progreſs, without falling into ſome great diſorder. <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> well obſerv'd, that prudence was given to man, inſtead of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, Walls, and Ramparts.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. NO vice more dangerous than that which beſt repreſents ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; yet are not men careful to avoid it, becauſe it is diſguis'd. It is a great conjunction of folly and vice, for one man to charge himſelf with the fault of another, that he may be
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33925:39"/>accounted innocent of the crime whereof he is guilty. He who coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances a fault, is more guilty than he who commits it; for there may be frailty in the one, but you cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt the other from malice.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. TO give a juſt Idea of the reaſon, wherewith it has pleas'd the Author of Nature to enlighten Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, methinks it may be ſaid, that the good uſe which is made of it gives birth, beauty, and perfection to all the vertues; and, that there are any Vices, proceeds from the abuſe of it. Can there be imagin'd a greater abuſe of reaſon, than to make uſe of it againſt it ſelf? I know there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but diſorder and abundance of confuſion amongſt the vices; but I know alſo they agree in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that they are always contrary to reaſon, and that they combine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to procure his ruine who is
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33925:40"/>content to be a ſlave thereto. How ſhameful is it to a man, to employ the directive lights of his minde, only to abaſe himſelf to the condition of animals?</p>
            <p n="20">XX. THere is nothing of greater diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to a man engag'd in vice, than, like a ſlave, to obey his paſſions; and his greateſt puniſhment is, that he cannot execute his deſigns: for he either wants confidence to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake what he deſires, or if he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it, he loſes his labour, and meets only with cares and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances. And ſo he is cruelly tortur'd by his own deſires; the hope of a pleaſure of ſhort continuance gives him a long ſuffering and Penance. In fine, it is a little ſweetneſs dearly bought, when a man muſt ſeek it with much danger in the midſt of a River of bitterneſs.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33925:40"/>
            <p n="21">XXI. INtereſt is a conſtant attendant of all the vices, but profit is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways of the retinue. Vice is not ſought for it ſelf, intereſt only enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges men to purſue it. Men are eaſily inclin'd to be corrupted by pride, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the honour conſequent thereto; by avarice, upon the ſcore of wealth; and by ſenſuality, upon that of pleaſure. There's no vice, but promiſes ſomewhat of good, and from which men do not expect ſome ſatisfaction: yet are they deceiv'd in that expectation, for the final iſſue of all is miſchief and misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. A Man ought to avoid evil, and recede from vice, out of aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and not only out of fear. I am content that he be called a fearful perſon, who eſchews evil without
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33925:41"/>having an extream horrour for it; but I ſhall never, upon that ſcore, account him juſt or vertuous. 'Tis an eaſie thing to ſay, that there is danger in becoming wicked; it muſt be added, that a man cannot be ſo without great injury to himſelf. Whoever lives ill, makes a real and moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable loſs; and he ought not only to fear, the danger wherein he involves himſelf, but if he hath common ſenſe about him, he ſhould always be in a trembling condition, becauſe his ruine is inevitable if he comply with his paſſions.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. VIces may in ſome manner take up part of our lives, but they deſerve not to employ it wholly. So that to give an exact definition of the lives of perſons addicted to Liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, it muſt be ſaid that it is but an imaginary phantaſm of life. When a man lives ill, he has nothing but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33925:41"/>the trouble, diſtraction, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of life, but not the true uſe of it. Idleneſs is nothing but the loſs of a man's life, and his abſolute ruine proceeds from the wicked actions whereto he is thereby addicted. There is a great difference between <hi>laſting</hi> and <hi>living.</hi> It may be ſaid of a man who grows old in crimes, that he has <hi>laſted</hi> a long time; but it cannot be ſaid he hath <hi>liv'd</hi> much. We muſt ſpeak otherwiſe of a young man full of honour, merits, and vertue, whom death ſnatches away in the flower of his age; for though he has <hi>laſted</hi> but a ſhort time, yet was his life <hi>long,</hi> ſince it was a noble one.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. IT is of no advantage to a wicked perſon to have conceal'd his crime; 'tis poſſible indeed that for a time he may have kept it from the knowledge of others, but what aſſurance has he that that ſecret will never be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd?
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33925:42"/>I ſay further, It is of little importance that men ſhould be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Evil we have done, ſince we are convinc'd of it our ſelves, and that God knows it; and therefore, if we are at eaſe on the one ſide, we ought to tremble on the other. We may indeed ſometimes ſecure our ſelves againſt the misfortunes and dangers which threaten us, but we cannot exempt our ſelves from a thouſand frights, nor avoid the endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of great loſſes.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. A Man is in greater danger than he imagines, when he leads an irregular life. A wicked man is ever in diſturbance; it ſignifies nothing to him, that all the world forgives him, ſince his own Conſcience ſuffers him not to be at reſt, and that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes carries his Tormenter about him. The very knowledge of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving liv'd ill, is a dreadful puniſhment to a vicious perſon.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:33925:42"/>
            <p n="26">XXVI. BE more careful and tender of your Conſcience, than of your Reputation. You are extreamly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to have Virtue, and yet it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies but little, to have it only in the opinion of men. A man ought to make no other account of himſelf, than according to what he effectually is; and he does not judge aright of himſelf, who does it by the character which is given him by others, who haply have but a ſlight knowledge of him.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. FRom the pleaſures and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Body, proceed the infirmities and indiſpoſitions of the Mind. When the Fleſh is too much made of, the Soul loſes its vigour; but if a man come to make a cuſtom of it, he will not have ſo much as the force to attempt what at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33925:43"/>ſeem'd moſt eaſie, and what he ſeriouſly deſir'd. He who is addicted to delights, cannot have a noble, gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and couragious Soul.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. WHen Pleaſure exceeds its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, it becomes a torture and a puniſhment. It may well be ſaid, That Virtue implies great advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſince Vice it ſelf is forc'd to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate it, to attain its end. Vice ſtudies the perſonation of Virtue in keeping certain meaſures, and in receding, at leaſt in appearance, from thoſe extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which are alwayes accounted an exceſs and irregularity.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. A Lyon loſes his fierceneſs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes tractable, the more he is flatter'd: but the Careſſes you make to your Body, render it more inſolent and obſtinate. Eat not to ſatisfie your Appetite, but only to ſatisfie the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33925:43"/>Hunger which torments you. Live not to eat, but eat in order to the preſervation of your life. Who eats little, is likely to live long. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of the Palate bring more to their deaths, than the edge of the Sword.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. VIces cannot cauſe any thing but diſguſt; and let men ſay what they will of it, they can never make any advantage thereof. There's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more prejudicial to the Body, than the exceſſive tenderneſs and love which men have for it. We find by experience, That Good cheer, and the other enjoyments which flatter the ſenſes, weaken the body, conſume the eſtate, impair health, and condemn the over-eager purſuers thereof to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite cares, troubles, and inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:33925:44"/>
            <p n="31">XXXI. WE may give this definition of Senſuality, That it is a ſweet and delightful beginning of a moſt bitter and fatal end. Vice cannot be inviſible to it ſelf; ſo that being aſham'd of its own deformity, it courts darkneſs, and hides it ſelf as much as may be. And yet hazard, which is inſeparable from fortune, is more favourable to it, than the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the darkeſt night.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. A Man addicted to pleaſure, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honours his body; and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive care he takes to humour it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes to him a ſource of afflictions, diſcontents, and maladies. Who flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters his Body, careſſes the fleſh, and gives himſelf over to pleaſure; gives confidence to his enemy, and arms him againſt himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33925:44"/>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. THe life of an unclean perſon, is a beſtial life: That of a man who onely minds his mouth, may juſtly be compar'd to the life attributed to Plants, which conſiſts onely in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſeeking of that nouriſhment which is proper for them.</p>
            <p n="34">XXXIV. PRide is nothing but a pompous excreſcency of Folly: for tell me, I pray, Whether there can be any thing more extravagant, than for one to be deſirous to enrich himſelf with a good that is purely accidental to him? I think I ſhould not injure a man in calling him a Fool, if he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects to be eſteem'd above others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is better clad, or has more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities in his cloſet. Mens merits never ought to depend on a good Taylor, or an excellent Goldſmith; but they are to be judg'd according to the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33925:45"/>ſtandard of virtue, and gallant acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. YOu would not excuſe him from the imputation of Folly, who, to get himſelf a heat, ſhould roll up and down in a great heap of Snow. Now a vain and preſumptuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is no leſs a Fool; for, to compaſs his end, he makes uſe of means that put him more and more from it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is highly conceited of his own merit and virtue, he would have all the world of the ſame perſuaſion; not conſidering, That if a man has all the moſt eminent qualifications, he renders himſelf contemptible, as ſoon as he thinks of having the advantage over all others.</p>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. OTher Vices covet to be in the dark, and to lie conceal'd; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pride loves the Noon-light; and it
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33925:45"/>is extravagant in this, That it would alwayes appear, as if whatever is in the world were much below it. And yet this, of all the Vices, ſeems to me the moſt to be abhorr'd.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. I Do not think any Sottiſhneſs equal to that of a vain perſon, and one that has an overweening opinion of himſelf; for whatever he thinks and does, is of no advantage to his Body, and withal extreamly prejudicial to his Soul. A man gains nothing in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vain-glorious, but the general ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and averſion of other men.</p>
            <p n="38">XXXVIII. WHatever we ſee here below, has a love for what is like it; only the vainglorious perſon has leſs averſion for another that is like him, than for death it ſelf. So that as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance begets love ſo a man who follows the dictates of Pride, oppoſes
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33925:46"/>Nature it ſelf. Pride is a ſavage Beaſt, an Enemy to Society, and pleas'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Solitude. This Vice is inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the Rich, and abſolutely abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in the Poor. When Pride faſtens it ſelf on a Rich man, it ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him a Fool: when it has the maſtery of a Poor man, it deprives him of ſenſe and reaſon.</p>
            <p n="39">XXXIX. WHat I am going now to ſay, is ſomewhat ſurprizing; but ſome advantage may be made of it againſt the diſorders and evils which Pride cauſes. To wit, That this Vice is ſo deteſtable, that being counter-balanc'd with the ſin, it makes us find a benefit in the very ſin it ſelf: And indeed it is ſometimes advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to an inſolent perſon, to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to ſome ugly miſcarriage, and ſuch as may in ſome meaſure humble him, that ſo he may diſengage himſelf from that mortal impoſtume of the mind.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33925:46"/>
            <p n="40">XL. A Man ſhould endeavour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worthy of honourable Employments, but not be over-earneſt to ſeek them: it is more glorious to deſerve them, without obtaining them, than to obtain them, without deſert. 'Tis a high piece of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to put in for an eminent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment with much forwardneſs, when a man is convinc'd of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs to manage it; but to make uſe of unjuſt means to attain it, is the greateſt infamy in the world. A man who raiſes himſelf by baſe wayes, rather falls, than is advanc'd.</p>
            <p n="41">XLI. GOd is the Author of all the good that's done in the world, and therefore the evil muſt proceed from your ſelf only. What occaſion then have you to boaſt ſo much? Is it of the evil you have done? That ſhould
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33925:47"/>produce nothing but ſhame and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy. Is it of the good? Conſider that as a thing purely accidental to you, and derived from another ſource. I would rather ſee you in an irregular courſe of life, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to an humble and ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, than vertuous, with a ſelf-ſatisfaction attended by Pride.</p>
            <p n="42">XLII AMbition ſtrayes, and miſſes the way that leads to true honour. Men come not to this by great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, nor by the other great Roads, through which Fortune ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily directs the Ambitious, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by following the Tracts of Virtue. And thus it happens, That, with all their fair pretenſions, they get further and further from what they deſire with ſo much earneſtneſs. How ſhould a man receive from Vice, that which Virtue only has the diſpoſal of, and which it never grants but to merit?</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33925:47"/>
            <p n="43">XLIII. BE miſtruſtful of Anger, becauſe it will endeavour to make you approve a wicked reſolution, as if it were the beſt counſel in the world. I ſay further, while it inclines you to do evil to others, it forces you to do the like to your ſelf. How many perſons could we inſtance in, who were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd becauſe they could not diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor take a word they were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at?</p>
            <p n="44">XLIV. THere's nothing ſo oppoſite to good Counſel, as an angry haſty humour; and therefore a man who is apt to be incens'd, is, methinks, highly oblig'd to conſult Prudence, and to ask advice before he ſpeaks. Will you not acknowledge, That a man ſhould have very ſtrong reaſons, ere he ſuffers his judgment to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him? I am ſeriouſly of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33925:48"/>That it argues as little reaſon in a man to ſuffer himſelf to be hurried away with the impetuous eruptions of Anger, as to be overcome with Drink.</p>
            <p n="45">XLV. IT is alwayes more ſafe for a man to pardon his Enemy, than to be reveng'd of him, and it is done with as little difficulty. You may pardon the injury you have receiv'd, without being oblig'd to ſtir a foot; whereas you muſt make many a ſtep, and run through a thouſand dangers, ere you can ſatisfie your paſſion.</p>
            <p n="46">XLVI. VVE muſt not expect any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer from a Carkaſs, nor true gratitude from a covetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The pleaſing paſſion he has of receiving, makes him forget what he has receiv'd. When he is to receive, the greateſt things ſeem very ſmall to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33925:48"/>him: but when he is oblig'd to give, the leaſt things ſeem very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and precious to him.</p>
            <p n="47">XLVII. OPen not your Soul to Avarice, unleſs you reſolve to lead a vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atious and miſerable life, when others rejoyce. If you hearken to that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed paſſion, it will make you endure all the inconveniencies of Poverty in the midſt of your gold and ſilver, and you will not ſo much live as languiſh. The condition of a covetous perſon is ſo unhappy, that the greateſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief you can wiſh him, is, that he ſhould live long.</p>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. THere are many things wanting to rich perſons, but it may be ſaid, That a covetous man wants all things; nay, he is ſo unfortunate, that he wants as well what he has, as what he has not, and poſſibly more:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33925:49"/>for he receives not the leaſt ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from what he is poſſeſs'd of, whereas he may find ſome ſweetneſs in deſiring what he has not yet. He gathers not the fruit of the goods whereof he is Maſter, and he has, at moſt, but the ſight and ſcent of the flowers he wiſhes.</p>
            <p n="49">XLIX. THere's a vaſt difference between a perſon who is afraid of pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and him who over-paſſionately is deſirous of wealth: Men would not willingly ſee the former, but the other they avoid as much as they can, and have a dreadful averſion for him. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity makes the former bold, and conceive direful deſigns; but Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, which is a baſe and infamous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, renders the latter deſpicable to all ſorts of perſons, becauſe he obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges none but his Heirs, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his intention.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:33925:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="50">L. THE extraordinary Affection which a covetous man has for the goods of this world, is as preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to him as a conflagration or ſhipwrack. For he has no benefit of what he is poſſeſs'd of, and it would be the ſame thing to him, if his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures had been conſum'd by fire, or buried in the Sea. Is not the Gold which ſtuffs his Coffers as good as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely loſt to him? Methinks it may be ſaid in a word of a covetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon poſſeſs'd of great Treaſures, That it is a well-furniſh'd kind of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty.</p>
            <p n="51">LI. A Covetous man is not beneficial to any one; he does much hurt to himſelf, he gives nothing to others, and yet deprives himſelf of all he could do, making himſelf the moſt unhappy of all men. In fine, he is
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33925:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>reduc'd to that extremity, as that he cannot do any good, but by ceaſing to live, and then his Heirs laugh at him in their mourning, and diſguiſe a real joy under a perſonated ſadneſs.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. A Covetous man never wants a reaſon to deny, whereas the truly-liberal perſon ever has one to give, even when there is nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of him. The former has no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the riches wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>of he is poſſeſs'd; the other mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> loſs, even when he deſpoils hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his friends. One is a ſlave to what he is poſſeſs'd of, but the other, by a ſurprizing effect of liberality, is ſtill Maſter of the good he hath given away.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. A Man muſt either have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his money, or the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney muſt be his Maſter; there is no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33925:50"/>mean between theſe two Extremities. Riches abuſe him who knows not how to make uſe of them as he ought.</p>
            <p n="54">LIV. ENvy hath this ill quality, That it rejoyces at the evil and ruine of others, without the leaſt advantage to it ſelf: ſo that it is not ſo much a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as a diſtraction, when, as it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly happens, it derives its own trouble and puniſhment, from the joy and content of others. How unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are they over whom this ſhameful paſſion is predominant! And how are they to be bemoan'd, ſince not only real Evils, but alſo whatever they diſcover that is good and advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in others, becomes their torment? The Evils of this life are but too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to make a man unhappy; but Envy is a double affliction, ſince the happineſs of others contributes to its torment.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:33925:51"/>
            <p n="55">LV. WE might fitly compare Envy to that kind of ſtone where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with men whet Knives: ſo Envy is good only to give an edge to the Tongue, yet is it of ſome advantage for one to be blam'd and reprov'd by an evil ſpeaker; and we commonly find that they who are wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to be Detractors, cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſpeaking againſt the moſt juſt and vertuous.</p>
            <p n="56">LVI. TIs better to be the mark of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, than the object of Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The condition of an envious perſon, is a thouſand times worſe than that of a man viſited with the Plague. Nay, ſome ſtick not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That it is better being poſſeſs'd with the Devil, than with Envy. We find-indeed that Envy is ill qualifi'd, which way ſoever we conſider it; the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33925:51"/>malice attending it is moſt abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the puniſhment conſequent thereto, is yet more ſtrange than is imagin'd.</p>
            <p n="57">LVII. VVE muſt ſay further, That Envy is a ſtrange Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; for being injuſtice it ſelf; as all know, yet is it however juſt in ſome manner. This requires explication. There's nothing ſo unjuſt as Envy, becauſe he who is infected therewith, thinks himſelf hurt by the virtue of others. But on the other ſide, there's nothing more juſt than Envy, becauſe it chaſtiſes him who hearkens to it, and follows it, condemning him to ſuch dreadful torments as ſurpaſs all imagination.</p>
            <p n="58">LVIII. THere's hardly any difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Flatterer who humours People, and a Wolf ſearching after a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33925:52"/>ſheep. He has not any love for the ſheep, and his looking after it, is only to make a prey of it. Be therefore miſtruſtful of a Flatterer, as of the moſt cruel of all your Enemies. The covetous perſon knows him better than any one. 'Tis too ſlight a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, to ſay, That Flattery is a refin'd kind of Lying; but it muſt be added, That it is an infamous piece of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery; for the wickedſt perſon in the world thinks it not much to ſpeak advantagiouſly of others, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them beyond his ability, when himſelf is therein concern'd: he has at that time all appearances of a real Friend, and he ſometimes makes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient diſcoveries thereof; and yet he does all the miſchief that an Enemy is capable of doing.</p>
            <p n="59">LIX. TIs a common Proverb, That a Lye has no feet; but I think it might be ſaid alſo, That a Lye has
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33925:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>wings, and that the Lyar has no feet. We find that Lying Travels poſt, and ſpreads it ſelf into ſeveral places of a ſudden; whereas a Lyar is as eaſily overtaken, as one who would run away having a Leg broken.</p>
            <p n="60">LX. A Man is never more Eloquent, than when he is in Neceſſity; and if ever he be likely to make uſe of far-fetch'd and extraordinary ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it muſt be when he finds himſelf obliged to repreſent his Exigencies. Truth is ſtronger than all Reaſons, and 'tis ſhe, to ſpeak properly, that keeps up the vigour of the mind. And yet men are commonly ſo indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, that they cannot digeſt, nay, hardly taſte the truth, if it be not a little diſguiz'd.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:33925:53"/>
            <p n="61">LXI. LOve cannot be legitimate or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, unleſs it hath good for its object. We do amiſs therefore in loving what is contrary to us, and what is not in a capacity to hurt us, but only when we place our affection on it. Muſt it not be a misfortune in Love, for one to love the cauſe of his misfortune? To this rank are they reduced, who love Fortune, and ſlight virtue.</p>
            <p n="62">LXII. THe ſerenity which the ſoul ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is in, and the joy it feels, is the fruit, or, if you pleaſe, the juſt recompence of her love. A man is not only happy when he directs his affections to wards good, but he alſo participates of the qualities of the thing beloved, and becomes truly good. The higheſt point of virtue conſiſts in loving God, and, let im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33925:53"/>and licentious perſons ſay what they pleaſe of it, there is no felicity equal to that of being loved by God.</p>
            <p n="63">LXIII. IS it not a great extravagance, to be paſſionately deſirous of goods, which being ſought by other perſons, will cauſe you a thouſand diſquiets? Nor is it a leſs, to have an affection for perſons who cannot be lov'd by others, without giving us much jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and a great diſturbance of mind. God only has this advantage above all the Creatures, that we may love and relie on him, without any fear of his being taken away from us. 'Tis an enormous Crime for one ſo much as to doubt the conſtancy of his friendſhip, for it is not likely he will ever forget us, or forſake us firſt.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:33925:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="64">LXIV. WHo loves a thing which he deſerves to loſe, becauſe he loves it, loves like a Fool, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate perſon. Now whoever loves Riches, deſerves to loſe them. Wiſh that you be accounted wiſe and prudent in love, and love only that which you will make your ſelf wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to poſſeſs, in loving it as you ought. Do you not know that love is the Bird-call of love, and that to be belov'd, is a very delicious bait, and an allurement that can hardly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected? Now friendſhip proceeds from both.</p>
            <p n="65">LXV. VVE are not to fear any thing but evil; ſince therefore all the evils of this life have only the appearance of being ſuch, there is no occaſion to fear them. The leaſt fault ought to make us tremble, but we
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33925:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhould not be ſtartled at labour. Sin is a real evil; labour is not an evil, as it is commonly imagined: nay, it is a real good, but not much in requeſt among effeminate and ſenſual per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: ſo that though opinion be not favourable to it, it fails not however of having truth of its ſide.</p>
            <p n="66">LXVI. REmember, that in the very things you eagerly purſue, there is more to be feared, than to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For example, when you have a ſtrong inclination to ſome pleaſure, how are you not more afraid of the gall intermixt in it, and the diſcontent which is inſeparable from it? You will poſſibly reſent it through the whole courſe of your life, whereas the ſatisfaction you have laſts not a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33925:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="67">LXVII. FEar and ſadneſs are not miſcall'd the blood of the wounded Soul. A man does not ſtand ſtill to look on the blood trickling from a wound, but bethinks himſelf of ſome ſudden remedy, and if poſſible, of binding it up. When you are threatned with ſome unwelcome accident, loſe not time in examining how heavy the blow will be, but rather think of the means to avoid it, or prepare your ſelf to receive it.</p>
            <p n="68">LXVIII. YOur diſgraces and miſeries will never ſeem ſo great to you, when you compare them with thoſe of others. The moſt afflicted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are eaſily comforted, when they reflect on what others endure; and it is an alleviation of the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies of this life, that we have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſufferers, and no man can ſay, he endures alone.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:33925:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="69">LXIX. SHame and Fear are careful and faithful enough in the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the goods of this life. Shame hath great power over the ſpirit of a perſon of quality, and commonly hinders him from doing any thing amiſs. The Populace is mindful of its duty through fear. The former motive argues a noble Soul, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Heart. The other betrayes a mean ſpirit; and thence we find, that it exerciſes its power, for the moſt part, over thoſe who are born to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude.</p>
            <p n="70">LXX. FEar is nothing but a kind a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent counſel, and a ſecret adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, which Nature gives all men, that they may ſecure themſelves againſt the evils which may attack and ſurprize them. Thoſe therefore which cannot be avoided, are not to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33925:56"/>be feared, ſince it is impoſſible to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them. Fear is good againſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but ſignifies nothing in Diſeaſes, no more than it does in the loſſes which men may have: but when they are certain of their coming, they muſt not then be diſcouraged, nor fear them with a certain weakneſs; but they ſhould rather expect them with an immoveable ſtedfaſtneſs of mind, and endure them with a truly heroick conſtancy.</p>
            <p n="71">LXXI. THe apprehenſion of evil, cauſes many times more grief, and a hundred times more diſquiet than the evil it ſelf when it comes. What unhappy accident ſoever happens, a man is ſmitten with it but once; and the blow being over, a man is free: whereas he who lives in continual fear, is ſubject to receive many. It therefore argues want of reaſon, to be alwayes in fear of an evil, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not laſt alwayes.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:33925:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="72">LXXII. A Man that fears, is not capable of undertaking many things; he readily believes whatever is ſaid to him. Fear checks the nobleſt projects in the World; and while a man heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens to it, he never executes the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he had taken. In fine, it makes ſuch a mutiny in mens imaginations, that they take the ſlighteſt ſuſpitions for manifeſt truths.</p>
            <p n="73">LXXIII. A Man muſt not compute the greatneſs of the danger by the fear he may have of it. It is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times dangerous to have much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. If you are deſirous to live in tranquillity, fear moderately, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not the opinion of ſome, who imagine to themſelves, that to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py upon earth, a man ſhould not be troubled at any thing.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:33925:57"/>
            <p n="74">LXXIV. THere is leſs prudence in hoping during the courſe of this life, than in fearing with wiſdom. Of evils there is a greater number and certainty than of goods. Diſeaſes, loſſes, diſgraces, and afflictions, are ſo frequent, that a man hardly hears any thing elſe ſpoken of, and it is rare to meet a man exempt from them. For one rich perſon, how many poor are there? The number of the happy is very ſmall, whereas that of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is almoſt infinite.</p>
            <p n="75">LXXV. TRue it is, Fear interprets things ill enough, yet has it this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that it never lies. It may be further ſaid, by way of excuſe, that it is a very difficult matter to avoid fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, when a man finds himſelf in danger. A man is more likely to be deceiv'd, when he hopes, in regard
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33925:57"/>the goods of this life are not ſo ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and that there are abundance of people perpetually in queſt of them.</p>
            <p n="76">LXXVI. NOt to have any hope, is to be the pooreſt of all Mankind. For he who has nothing to hope, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to the utmoſt of all neceſſities. How would you have a man to be in a capacity of having ſome good, when he has loſt hope, which is the laſt of all goods?</p>
            <p n="77">LXXVII. PAſt enjoyments do not alleviate preſent evils; whereas the evils a man has endur'd, heighten the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſatisfactions. An expected good is not truly a good; evil enſur'd with patience is no longer evil, and as ſoon as it ceaſes, 'tis chang'd into pleaſure, and gives the conſtant bearer of it much ſatisfaction.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33925:58"/>
            <p n="78">LXXVIII. YOu will never be deceived, when you ſhall regulate your joy and grief according to the things themſelves. Uſe them ſo, as not to be exceſſively afflicted at what amounts to almoſt nothing; nor to be over-glad, when there is but ſmall occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for it. Prudence would have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain meaſures obſerved in the liberty granted to our paſſions, and we muſt not, upon the leaſt occaſions that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves, ſuffer them to act to the full extent they may have. Take a little leaſure to conſider what fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens you; perhaps you will not fear it at all, when you ſhall have reflected on it; at leaſt the apprehenſion you have of it will not be ſo great. Why, I pray, are you ſo caſt down, and what is it that ſo much afflicts you? Have the patience to examine it, and you will certainly find, that there is ſome exceſs of your ſide, and that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33925:58"/>the occaſion is ſo trivial, that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves not you ſhould conceive any grief thereat. Your fear is not ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, ſince all the ſufferings of this life, and what muſt have its period with time, ought not to diſturb a man, who makes it his glory to be guided by the dictates of reaſon.</p>
            <p n="79">LXXIX. TIs not the greateſt miſery of man, as ſome imagine, to have death for his enemy, and to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſtrugling with it during this life; but it conſiſts in this, That his coming into this world, is only in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to deſtroy himſelf. He is his own moſt cruel enemy, and having ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily too great an affection for life, he becomes a ſlave to all Vices; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if he had a ſtrong apprehenſion of death, he would not be ſo backward, in endeavouring to become a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, and conſequently very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:33925:59"/>
            <p n="80">LXXX. VVHoever would free himſelf from the apprehenſion of evil, has no more to do, than to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf to the doing of that which is good, and that continually. Eſchew evil, that you may have a right to hope for good. A man bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits himſelf when he obliges others. You do more injury than you imagine, when you mind only your own concerns and intereſt: if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean your ſelf ſo, none will be ready to aſſiſt you in a time of neceſſity. It's no great commendation to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear doing evil to any one; in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving others, a man does not only pleaſure them, but he alſo obliges him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Make as many Friends as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly you can. <hi>Attalus</hi> ſaid, It was a greater pleaſure to make Friends, than to have ſuch; and I add, That it is many times more advantagious.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:33925:59"/>
            <p n="81">LXXXI. THe goodneſs, or integrity of the Soul, which we know under the precious and amiable name of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, implies the not committing of any fault; and Juſtice has for its mark, the not injuring of any body. Yet, to ſay truth, is not this but one part of Charity; to make it complete, we muſt add mercifulneſs thereto. And indeed the luſtre of this virtue, which does not permit the offending of any one, is admirably heightned by the noble effuſions of liberality.</p>
            <p n="82">LXXXII. THe love of your ſelf ought to be the ſtandard and module of your juſtice; by judging others by your ſelf, you cannot be deceived, in regard you conſider their perſons, goods, affairs, and concerns, as if all were your own. 'Tis a kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, for one to imagine, that he has
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33925:60"/>highly obliged a perſon, when he hath done him no harm. Juſtice does not require any acknowledgment; and I ſhould do ill to brag that I had done a man a kindneſs, meerly becauſe I had forborn to offend him.</p>
            <p n="83">LXXXIII. TO ſuſpect evil ſometimes, and to be miſtruſtful of it, may paſs for a piece of wiſdom; but to believe it without any ground, argues light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. There is prudence in the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of a mans judgment, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, in keeping it ſecret. Be wary in framing your judgment alwayes according to the teſtimony of the ſenſes; they may eaſily be ſurprized, but you ſhould be careful not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Never therefore declare your thoughts haſtily upon any matter whatſoever; time will inſtruct you, and diſcover the truth to you, that you may afterwards do the like to others.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:33925:60"/>
            <p n="84">LXXXIV. JUſtice without Clemency, comes near Cruelty; and Clemency with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Juſtice, is a very dangerous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence. True it is, we ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes aſſign the firſt rank to Juſtice; but Lenity, Meekneſs and Clemency ought to attend it; nay, we ought to give them a greater extent. Juſtice is a quality ſo noble and precious, that it ought to be commended even when it is not ſupported by prudence; whereas prudence, without the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of juſtice, has neither merit, nor luſtre. Juſtice has this advantage, that being alone, it is ſtill very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious; but prudence can only hurt, when it is not ſupported by juſtice. There is no venom more dangerous than that of Serpents; ſo we receive greateſt harm from thoſe whoſe arms conſiſt moſt in ſubtleties and inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:33925:61"/>
            <p n="85">LXXXV. WHen a man purſues only what can give him ſatisfaction, 'tis a difficult matter for him to meet with what is good and beneficial. If the will have the ſupremacy over reaſon, it will make him conceive ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. 'Tis not poſſible for him to be juſt, while he is govern'd by ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Conſider not the perſons, look only on the merit; think it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to examine who has the right of his ſide, without reflecting on your own power, or complying with your own particular inclination.</p>
            <p n="86">LXXXVI. TIs an additional degree to ones malice, for him to do evil, only becauſe he loves it; but it is a very great progreſs in wickedneſs, to love the evil, becauſe he has done it. It is only the part of a Fool to become wicked, that he may do harm to thoſe
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33925:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>that are ſuch; and it argues a clear loſs of judgment, for a man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce virtue, becauſe he has an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for thoſe who love Vice.</p>
            <p n="87">LXXXVII. A Man muſt have a great ſtock of courage and reſolution, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſhame; but he comes to the higheſt pitch of generoſity, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers not himſelf to be brought down by neceſſity. Whoever has the courage to make head againſt that, acquires no leſs glory than he who overcomes himſelf.</p>
            <p n="88">LXXXVIII. TRue generoſity does not conſiſt in the undertaking of many bold and difficult things, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly enduring all the evils that happen. There's no power ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute upon earth, but ſometimes meets with reſiſtance; but patience conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues alwayes firm and immoveable,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33925:62"/>and nothing can be done againſt it. To ſay that one will not ſupport ſome diſaſtrous accident, or ſome injury, is to ſpeak like Women, and to make too viſible a diſcovery of weakneſs. A man ſpeaks otherwiſe, and ſayes with a generous reſolution, I will not do it.</p>
            <p n="89">LXXXIX. GReat difficulties do only animate ſuch as have courage; the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes that happen to them, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover what they are. They know not what it is to hearken to Fear, being perſuaded that a generous and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Soul can triumph over all its enemies. It muſt be confeſs'd, that patience is wonderfully ſtrong, ſince it compaſſes all without being aſſiſted by any one. 'Tis a fortreſs that defends it ſelf, and ſtands not in any need of anger, to force off ſuch as attack it.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:33925:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="90">XC. FOrtitude and Prudence are the two virtues that ſupport the magnificent Chariot wherein. Victory is ſeated. A man is doubly fortifi'd, when he knows how to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of generoſity and good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. How gallant and daring ſoever a man may be, yet cannot he be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful long in his enterprizes, if he be not reliev'd by prudence.</p>
            <p n="91">XCI. MEdiocrity muſt infallibly be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the rank of the virtues, becauſe it keeps conſtantly in the middle. The other virtues, to be true ones, muſt, with much care and pains, ſeek for that which medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity has naturally. Its name ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently diſcovers, That it is a virtue which alwayes takes up the middle or mean, which all the other virtues en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to get into. There's nothing
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33925:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>more true than what I am going to ſay, though it be ſomewhat ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing: What is call'd the leaſt in the moral virtues, is what's moſt great and moſt excellent therein; the exceſs juſtly paſſes for a defect, and medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity is acknowledged a rare virtue. Moderation ſeaſons all things; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it the ſweeteſt and moſt pleaſant become bitter and inſupportable: It keeps up honour, it offers pleaſures and enjoyments that are pure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent. In a word, we are to look on it as the ſource and principle of whatever there is that is good, of good repute, and beneficial amongſt men.</p>
            <p n="92">XCII. A Moderate man has alwayes a ſufficient Eſtate. And as the paſſions ruine us by the exceſſive expences we are obliged to be at to ſatisfie them; ſo our receſſion from Vices contributes not a little to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33925:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>us. A man acquires much, when he is at no ſuperfluous expence. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration therefore is not only a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but a great treaſure alſo. Dice and Women conſume more wealth than a great Conflagration; and of all the engagements a man may have in the world, I think there's none ſtronger, and more hard to get out of, than Gaming and Debauchery.</p>
            <p n="93">XCIII. A Man ſhould not for any other reaſon care much for his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, than that he cannot live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; ſince therefore you do not live for it, trouble not your ſelf ſo much to ſatisfie it. Regulate its ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations according to its exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, and not according to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions it craves. Men would not be ſubject to ſo many diſeaſes, if they treated their bodies with leſs tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than they do.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:33925:64"/>
            <p n="94">XCIV. DEath is an excellent Picture, which faithfully repreſents vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Let him who would learn to live well, conſult the dead. True Philoſophy is nothing but a ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon death: let us make uſe of its precepts, that we may diſcover the deformity of Vice, and the vanity of all things in the world; let us alſo follow the Rules it gives us, to make a great progreſs, in a ſhort time, in the ſtudy and exerciſes of virtue.</p>
            <p n="95">XCV. YOu will never better remember your ſelf, than when you ſhall think that ſome day you muſt dye. The conſideration of death is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably fruitful: for it teaches us what we are now, it ſhews us what we ſhall be one day, and it inſtructs us what we ought to do during the courſe of this life. In fine, death is the moſt exact
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33925:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>rule of mens lives, and it does them more good than they imagine to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="96">XCVI. IMagine not that at your death you ſimply ceaſe to live; I ſay, that it is then you ceaſe to dye. True it is, you began to live the firſt day you came into the world; but from that day alſo you began to dye; you made but one entrance into both life and death: the light which enlightens your life, is like that of a Candle; what keeps it in, conſumes it.</p>
            <p n="97">XCVII. PRay, tell me, what was man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was born? You will grant, he was not. Now I hold that to be the greateſt and moſt inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table of all neceſſities. And what is he who a little before was not, and who after he hath received being, is n a manner nothing, and who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33925:65"/>in a ſhort time will be but a little heap of duſt and aſhes? It muſt be acknowledged, That all theſe things conſidered in themſelves, are extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſpicable; only virtue compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends ſo much greatneſs and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that it is able to exalt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble whatever approaches it. Let us therefore eſteem that above all things, which only can render us ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p n="98">XCVIII. THere is no difference between living long, and ſuffering long. Afflictions, troubles, tears and griefs are born with us. The life of man is but a long and tedious ſeries of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, evils, and torments; but man has ſome reaſon to comfort himſelf, ſince that when he begins to live, he immediately begins to approach his end, and to make ſome advancement towards death.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:33925:65"/>
            <p n="99">XCIX. VIrtue receives no leſs luſtre from the misfortunes which befal the followers of Vice, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the wicked commonly ſuffer, than from the ſolid enjoyments and ſatisfactions which good men many times feel, in the exerciſe of the moſt difficult virtues. He muſt needs be the moſt miſerable perſon in the world, who has a Soul that ſerves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to keep his body alive, and does not regulate its motions. It may well be ſaid, this being acknowledged, That the Soul is to the body, but as ſalt to meat, which it exempts from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption only for a time.</p>
            <p n="100">C. VIrtue is but an accident to man, to ſpeak as the Philoſophers do; yet does that accident preſerve his ſubſtance. All things were created by God for the ſervice of man, and he
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33925:66"/>created man, that he might receive honour and ſervice from him, as well as from all the reſt of the Creatures. 'Tis virtue that renders us capable of ſerving and honouring him, who hath vouchſafed to bring us out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and without it we cannot pleaſe our Creator.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33925:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>STOICAL MAXIMES.</head>
            <p n="1">I. IT is not what's poſſeſſed that gives ſatisfaction, but what one loves. In like manner, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content of moſt men proceeds not from what is wanting to them, but from what they deſire. He who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires nothing, may be as happy as he who has all the accommodations in the world. To be free from all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, is a treaſure to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an Empire. How many things are there which may be wanting to the greateſt Kings upon earth? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a man who deſires not any thing, can never be ſaid to be indigent.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:33925:67"/>
            <p n="2">II. JOy is not within the juriſdiction of Fortune, ſhe cannot, when ſhe pleaſes, make us a preſent of it: 'tis a moveable belonging to the heart, not only becauſe it cannot be met withal elſewhere, but alſo becauſe there only it has its birth. They are not the things which pleaſe us that create our pleaſure and ſatisfaction; nor are thoſe which diſturb us, the cauſe of our diſquiet; we muſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call our own will to an account, that being the right ſource from which joy, pleaſure, vexation and ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs proceed. Thence it comes, that what is pleaſing to one, is extremely unpleaſant to another. 'Tis not to be attributed to the variety of things, but to the diverſity of our wills, that our hearts entertain ſo many affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons oppoſite one to the other.</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:33925:67"/>
            <p n="3">III. TIs an errour common to all men, that they would attain felicity by following wayes which cannot lead them thereto. How can they arrive at the point of not deſiring any thing, while they take the way of deſires? Would you ſpare your ſelf abundance of trouble and pains-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king? Regulate your concupiſcence, have no violent inclination for any thing whatſoever. When a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires nothing beforehand, he is in no fear of being unhappy, and he comes to the end of his Journey, without being at any pains by the way. The true felicity of a man upon earth, conſiſts rather in the not-poſſeſſion of any thing, than in being numbred among the living. Let us once in good earneſt renounce all our deſires, ſince it is a thing within our power.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:33925:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="4">IV. THe way for a man to free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from many troubles, cares, and vexations, is, not to fear, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire any thing. All your unhappineſs, if you reflect on it, proceeds only from your not having what you wiſh, or haply from the hapning of ſomething to you which is not conſonant to your inclination. You will have no diſgraces to overcome, while your heart preſerves its freedom, and all things are indifferent to it.</p>
            <p n="5">V. THe more the affection is ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd in us, the more the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content abates. A man is never fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from falling into affliction, than when he feels his will at liberty, and not bent by any ſtrong inclination. To make an exchange of inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is the moſt eaſie and moſt certain way to get out of miſery. Adjuſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33925:68"/>your deſires to all ſorts of emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and you will ſurmount the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt difficulties without any trouble. Vexation is rather taken than given.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. TIs a great art to know how to deſire; unleſs a man be very well vers'd in it, he cannot live con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly. He who can moderate his deſires, is above all, and the whole world has not any thing worthy of him. It is an eaſie matter for one to find perfect repoſe here below, and to keep at a diſtance from him the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate accidents which render life burthenſom and inſupportable: all that's to be done, is, to have an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute independency to all creatures, and to be raiſed above ones ſelf. There are ſome, who, having loſt their fight, and the uſe of hands and feet, yet live in much content. Make not therefore your happineſs to depend either on the body, or on any thing
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33925:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>that can flatter the ſenſes. A Crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple does not ſo much as think of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining at his lameneſs, when his heart is ſatisfied. He that can beſt be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf, cares but little for all the reſt. You may be extreamly rich with the good uſe of your will.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. TIs a great imprudence to love without choice and diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; a man ſhould be careful where he places his affection. If he deſire confuſedly, and in the groſs, he cannot avoid being deceived; and the ill ſucceſs which our deſires have had, fills us with ſadneſs and affliction, out of which we can hardly recover our ſelves. If you deſire what is within another mans power, you run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of getting nothing thereby but diſpleaſure; whereas if you wiſh on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what depends on your ſelf, you will run no hazard of your ſatisfaction. Endeavour that your will have not
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33925:69"/>any bent but for thoſe things which are within its juriſdiction. And what is there that more abſolutely depends on it, than the deſire of being a good man, and of employing it ſelf only in vertuous and praiſe-worthy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. PLeaſure conſiſts in the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the deſire; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ought ſo to regulate your will, as that it ſhould wiſh only thoſe things which it can compaſs, without giving her deſires the freedom to reach at thoſe things which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. You will be the happieſt of all men, if you meaſure your inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, affections and deſires, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the power you have: if you recede from this rule, you will be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable as often as you ſhall deſire any thing.</p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:33925:70"/>
            <p n="9">IX. IF you can ſatisfie your appetite with a little meat, you will be thought extravagant, if you deſire to eat much, to augment hunger, and irritate you appetite. The caſe will be the ſame with you, when, though you can be ſatisfied in deſiring but few things, yet you inconſiderately ſlacken the reins of your will, which minds not content, becauſe ſhe is hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with a monſtrous exceſs to deſire whatever is contrary to her own repoſe. That of concupiſcence, is a ſphere of a prodigious extent. Our hearts ſooner find tranquillity and content in not deſiring any thing, than in making great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:33925:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="10">X. HE who is come to the point of not-fearing any thing, and of not-hoping any thing, has made a moſt conſiderable Acqueſt: the peace and ſerenity he enjoyes, is a Preſent, which Fortune, as rich as ſhe is, is not able to make him; a man by this means may become his own Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor. He may procure to himſelf more ſatisfaction, in not deſiring any thing, than he ſhould receive from the conqueſt of the whole world. 'Tis well known, there have been ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous perſons who have looked on the world with contempt; but all the people upon earth paſſionately wiſh themſelves as happy as he who has given over deſiring any thing in this world. That is the ſolid content, and true felicity of our hearts.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:33925:71"/>
            <p n="11">XI. IF your courage be ſo great, as that you are reſolved to ſuffer, be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, you will deliver your ſelf from a heavy burthen of cares, ſince you will ſhake off impatience, which cannot be better defined, than by ſaying, that it is as 'twere the thread which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens all evils together; or rather as the point, which opens a paſſage to diſgraces and misfortunes in our Souls. Impatience does not diminiſh, but alwayes augment the evil.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. ADd not a ſecond evil to that which you already endure, by ſuffering your ſelf to be overcome with impatience. Whoever does not ſupport his misfortune with patience, beſides the fault he commits, if further obliged to wade through a ſecond trouble, much greater and more bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſom than the former.</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:33925:71"/>
            <p n="13">XIII. MEn are exempted from rage and deſpair, when they pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſuffer the evils that happen; but they feel a moſt undiſturbed joy, when they apply themſelves to do well. There is no ſatisfaction equal to that which proceeds from a good action.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. KEep your heart free and diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged from paſſions, and you will be greater than <hi>Alexander;</hi> you will not be enſlaved to any one, whereas that Monarch was ſo to his paſſions. I would rather be reduced to the condition of the moſt wretched Captive, than that any paſſion ſhould domineer over me.</p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:33925:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="15">XV. I Make no difficulty to prefer the freedom of the heart before the Empire of the whole world. A man is not yet free, while he is ſtrugling with his paſſions, and is engaged againſt his own inclinations. He who obeys his paſſions, is at the ſame time a ſlave to ſeveral Tyrants.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. IT is no ſmall victory to conquer a paſſion. 'Tis more glorious for a man to triumph over his own heart, than to take a Cittadel by ſtorm; provided he be obliged for that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt only to Virtue, and not to Chance, and the impetuoſity of ſome other paſſion. For there are ſome Vices that are mutually-deſtructive one to another: ſo that to employ one Vice to chaſe away another, is not ſo much a victory, as a ſhameful defeat.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:33925:72"/>
            <p n="17">XVII. WHen two Vices are conteſting in our Souls, and one has the victory over the other, it cannot be ſaid that it is forced thence, but only kept in reſtraint, ſo as that upon the firſt occaſion it flies out again, and becomes more inſolent than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. TO lop off the branches of a Tree, and to leave the ſtock in a thriving condition, is to take much pains to no purpoſe. Virtue is ill grafted in a heart, where the root of Vice thrives. One paſſion does not deſtroy another paſſion; one Vice does not ſmother another Vice.</p>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:33925:73"/>
            <p n="19">XIX. THere are ſome forlorn and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched perſons, who have a horrour for certain Vices, not out of any pleaſure or ſatisfaction they find in Virtue, but by reaſon of the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation they have to ſome other Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 'Tis a ſtrange unhappineſs, to conceive a ſtrong diſguſt to evil, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loving the good.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. THere is nothing more ſtrange, yet more true, than what I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſay, to wit, That the Vices which moſt reſemble Virtue, are thoſe which a man ought moſt carefully to avoid, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y are a thouſand times more dangerous than the reſt. An enemy that diſguiſes himſelf under the vail of ſincere Friendſhip, is much more to be feared, than he who declares open hoſtility. We ſhall doubtleſs fall into the traps of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33925:73"/>Virtues, unleſs we cleanſe our Souls of all ſorts of affections, paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and deſires.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. THe Maſter-piece of life conſiſts in knowing that which is good, and how to love it. Cares, troubles, and afflictions enter into the Soul at thoſe two gaps, and all our misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune proceeds either from our not judging rightly of things, or not well regulating our affections. Paſſion makes us eagerly deſire that which is evil, and ignorance hinders our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing between good and evil.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. LEt us be alwayes guided by truth, never by opinion. Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and deceit commonly make evils appear greater than they really are; and were it not for thoſe two, men would not think any thing over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthenſom in the world.</p>
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33925:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="23">XXIII. WE many times rejoyce at what we ſhould bewail, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bewail what we ſhould laugh at. One while we ſeem to be ſad, another while glad, though we have no occaſion to expreſs either grief or joy. We ſhould rather bluſh at our weakneſs, conſidering that ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial things make ſo much impreſſion on our Souls.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. APparent evils do commonly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment us more cruelly than the real; and it may be ſaid, That what cauſes ſadneſs, affliction, and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, is not ſo much the evil that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, as that which we imagine muſt happen. Opinion deceives and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons us.</p>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:33925:74"/>
            <p n="25">XXV. WE account Wealth a good, and in that we do not judge rightly of it; that name is to be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated only to the good uſe which is made thereof, when we make a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent diſpenſation of what is in it ſelf the occaſion of much evil.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. IF there be any good in Riches, 'tis very inconſiderable; for they give us a great bent to veil, involving thoſe that are poſſeſſed thereof in a thouſand dreadful dangers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning them to many cares, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and diſturbances: they are the fuel of Concupiſcence, and of all the Vices; they cauſe diſquiet to thoſe that deſire them; they alſo who are poſſeſſed of them, are in perpetual fear of their getting away from them: in fine, they who have loſt them, are hardly recoverable out of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:33925:75"/>
            <p n="27">XXVII. POverty is the greateſt of all goods, becauſe it does not hurt any but him that avoids it, and has an averſion for it; whereas Riches moſt dangerouſly hurt thoſe who over-paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately love them. If any one ſay, That Poverty is extreamly incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious we muſt anſwer him, that the incommodiouſneſs is not annex'd to Poverty, but to the perſon of him who is poor.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. TIs a very groſs errour to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that a man is very happy, becauſe poſſeſſed of great treaſures; and that men ſhould make a greater account of him, than of ſuch as are poor. I affirm, on the contrary, that he is more miſerable, than ſuch as are not poſſeſſed of any thing at all; for the greater his Riches are, the greater are his Exigencies. What is wanting
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:33925:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>to a poor man? Nothing in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; her is content when he has food and rayment, whereas there are a thouſand things wanting to a rich man, to feed his Luxury, Pride, and Vanity.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. RIch men are reduced to great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, ſince whatever they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is wanting to them; whereas the poor man wants only what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. A rich man has ſo many exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies as he hath paſſions and vices to feed. A poor man minds only his ſuſtenance. I call a man poor, be he as rich as may be otherwiſe, when he has need of all he is poſſeſſed of. I call a man rich, how miſerable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he may appear, when he ſtands not in need of all thoſe things that are out of his power. Many are poor with all their treaſures, becauſe they know not how to be content with little.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:33925:76"/>
            <p n="30">XXX. THey who deſire riches only in order to voluptuouſneſs, are meanly-ſpirited, and infamous; they who hope to acquire honour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, are extreamly deceived. In fine, they who ſeek them, only in order to the ſatisfaction of their paſſions, are guilty of a great fault; but they who propoſe to themſelves no other deſign in the acqueſt thereof, than to exempt themſelves from neceſſity, ought to remember, that the eaſieſt way to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, is to be content with few things. I affirm further, That for a man to be clearly exempted from ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, all he has to do, is to forbear deſiring any thing.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:33925:76"/>
            <p n="31">XXXI. I Cannot deny but that health is a great good, yet would I have all acknowledge that ſickneſs is not a very great evil. This teaches men to know themſelves, whereas health de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives them, by making them imagine they ſhall never dye. Is it any evil for one to know by experience, that he is a man? How many, think you, are now very well, who yet are nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer death, than ſome that are given over by the Phyſicians? Do we not daily ſee, That ſome weak, tender, and infirm perſons, live longer than others who ſeem to be of a moſt healthful conſtitution?</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. LIfe is a good, when it is well employ'd; Death never ought to be called a great evil, ſave only when a man has not lived well. Death is not a miſcarriage, but a very
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33925:77"/>natural thing. It has been a great misfortune to many, that they have lived long. He never dyes too ſoon, who has lived as a perſon of repute, and perſiſted in the exerciſe of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. A Man does not loſe his life, though death come ſooner than he expected it; for he who affirms that he loſes what he owes, ſeems wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling abſolutely to deny his debt, at the very time that he payes it. We come into the world by the portal of life, but upon condition that we ſhould go out of it by that of death.</p>
            <p n="34">XXXIV. WE ſhould not ſtand ſo much in fear of death, ſince we dye daily. When a man dyes, he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ceaſes to live; and when he comes into the world, he begins to dye. To
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:33925:77"/>ſay that we ſhall dye one day, is not a thing more certain than to affirm, that we ſhall dye every moment of our life. Would that man paſs for a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional perſon, who ſhould deny to do that once only, which he is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally doing? Fear not therefore to dye. If death ſurprize you in the flower of your age, it will bury a thouſand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with you; if it delayes its coming till old age, it will then deliver you out of many infirmities.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. THe good there may be in honour is great or mean, anſwerably to what it is imagined. Make little account of opinion; eſteem truth above all things: Never be diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at mens not-ſpeaking advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of you, eſpecially if they be ill-livers, and ſuch as indifferently revile all ſorts of perſons. If they ſpeak the truth, I think you have no reaſon to grumble or complain: If they do
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33925:78"/>not, they ſuffer by it more than you do; do not you therefore imitate them; and if you are ſometimes forc'd to ſpeak of them, do it in civil, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and obliging terms. When they ſpeak ill of you, you may eaſily ſlight their diſcourſes, and not ſo much as reflect on them; but how much ſoever you may endeavour to content and pacifie them, you will never compaſs it.</p>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. A Perſon who truly deſerves to be commended, ſhould never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern himſelf at mens not doing him that juſtice; but a man ſhould ever beware deſiring applauſe, when he conceives himſelf unworthy of it. It ſignifies little to commend a man, he is not the more virtuous for that; but it argues his effectually being ſuch, when he deſerves the approbation of good people. To commend a perſon who has neither virtue nor merit
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33925:78"/>amounts to as much as to put a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſluire upon him. Merit alone, without Elogies, is a rare virtue, and of great value. Envy faſtens it ſelf only on great and noble qualities.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. YOur troubles will ſeem leſs bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to you, if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with thoſe of others. Are you deſirous not to endure ſo much? Suffer with patience the diſgraces that happen to you: if your frailty take their part againſt you, fortifie your own with reaſon. If thoſe troubles happen through your own fault, receive them as a thing that was due to you; if you have not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed thereto, be ſatisfi'd with the thought of your innocency, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear repining, leſt you fall into ſome fault.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:33925:79"/>
            <p n="38">XXXVIII. A Man who has loſt what he much eſteemed, and has not loſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, has no great occaſion to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted; Riches had made him a loſt man, had he not loſt them. We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call that diſgrace and misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which is an excellent remedy for our evils; and we look on that as a very great loſs, which many times is of great benefit to us. It may be ſaid of a man that has loſt his Goods, that he is alſo loſt himſelf. We have known more people undone, becauſe they had an Eſtate, than becauſe they had abſolutely loſt all. 'Tis the part of a Robber to take away what is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans; To ſecure ones treaſures with much diſquiet, is the buſineſs of a covetous perſon. To beg Money, argues Poverty; To be afflicted at the want of it, argues the condition of a miſerable perſon. I know too well, that a man thinks himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33925:79"/>when he fins himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoiled of all he has, be it by what accident ſoever; but I know alſo, that he is deceived, and that he has no cauſe to complain, for what he looks on as an inſupportable diſgrace, is commonly the ſource of his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="39">XXXIX. IT argues little judgment in us, to be out of humour, becauſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing has happened to us contrary to our expectation. We ſhould not have hoped to obtain that which no-body had promiſed us. We are not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, we are not ſecured of any thing in this world. 'Tis the ordinary ſtyle, and the moſt common and moſt generally-received Law amongſt men, every moment almoſt for us to ſee things which diſturb us. Which way ſoever we turn our ſelves, we meet with nothing but diſgraces and misfortunes, which men muſt work
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:33925:80"/>their way through, though ever ſo unwilling to do it. Has any one among us been promis'd an uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted happineſs, without the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of any misfortune? In the diſgraces that have happen'd to you, never conſider the loſs they have caus'd you, but reflect only on the danger you have avoided, inaſmuch as he who has loſt all he was poſſeſs'd of, has yet ſome reaſon to be comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nay, indeed to rejoyce, ſince he was not loſt himſelf with his wealth.</p>
            <p n="40">XL. YOu ought not to account things ever the better, becauſe you have earneſtly deſir'd them. Trouble, many times, is the fruit and reſult of deſire, and a man may be happy in not-obtaining all he wiſhes. Be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſtful of your will; it deceives the underſtanding, and it commonly miſtakes in the choice it makes of things. 'Tis not inclination, but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33925:80"/>ought to be our directreſs in all ſorts of occurrences.</p>
            <p n="41">XLI. VVE ſhould not make any great account of any thing in this world, ſince they who are the moſt upright Judges thereof, declare, That it is more glorious to ſlight them, through greatneſs of courage, than for a man to acquire them by his own induſtry.</p>
            <p n="42">XLII. LIfe, with ſin, is a kind of death; without the pleaſure attending ſin, 'tis a tedious night; with joy, 'tis but an hours ſpace; with cares and troubles, 'tis an age; with hope, 'tis a pleaſant ſlumber; or rather a dream. In fine, to ſpeak of Life as we ought to do, we ſhould never call it by that name, ſave only when it has the attendance of virtue. Life ſeems very ſhort to the fortunate,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33925:81"/>and of a ſtrange length to the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. The beſt dayes are ſooneſt gone, and ſlide away impercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly.</p>
            <p n="43">XLIII. HE that can well endure, may without difficulty overcome. To ſuffer and overcome, relate to the ſame Science. Patience is an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Miſtreſs to teach both; and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, with all her power, is obliged to yield to it.</p>
            <p n="44">XLIV. AS all the other ſenſes preſuppoſe that of Touching, ſo do all the virtues preſuppoſe patience; and we may ſay it is an unexhauſtible ſource, whence all actions that have any thing of goodneſs in them, take their riſe.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:33925:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="45">XLV. VVHo deſires to find but little trouble in the labour he is unwillingly oblig'd to go through, muſt ſeek it of the forementioned Miſtreſs; for a man more willingly and readily endures an evil whereto he has been already accuſtomed. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience does not only contribute to the acqueſt of prudence in a man, but it promotes alſo his attaining of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
            <p n="46">XLVI. TAke a fancy to have but few things, and you will find in the miſery of others a rich treaſure for your ſelf. Poverty is not a virtue; only the love of poverty deſerves that noble name.</p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:33925:82"/>
            <p n="47">XLVII. A Man will find Poverty a moſt cruel Enemy, when he has no affection at all for it: for not to mention the inconveniences attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, it opens a gap to many other diſaſtrous evils. Neceſſity and ſhame are two inexhauſtible ſources of evils and misfortunes.</p>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. THough Riches conſider'd in themſelves are not evil, yet are they alwayes very dangerous, and conſequently deſerve to be ſlighted. Hire is good for a hundred things, but not amidſt a great heap of Powder. The ſame may be ſaid of Riches, they become evil as ſoon as the Will fixes it ſelf upon them.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:33925:82"/>
            <p n="49">XLIX. GOld cauſes ſtrange diſorders, when it does not fall into good hands. Would you know when it is good? when a man is at a diſtance from it. If he who is its Maſter be deſirous to make any advantage of it, the onely way is preſently to be rid of it. Another thing may be ſaid upon this ſubject of Gold, is, That the perſon who refuſes it, deſerves no leſs applauſe, than he who would give it.</p>
            <p n="50">L. TWas not ill ſaid of Riches, when one called them Fortune's vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: now certain it is, that what comes up out of the entrails with any violence, is already ſpoiled and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; whence it comes, that the leaſt queaſy-ſtomack'd cannot look on it without horrour.</p>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:33925:83"/>
            <p n="51">LI. COnſider all the goods of this world as meer Caſualties; No man can brag that Fortune has any dependance on him. We ſhould never put virtue into the rank of our goods, unleſs we have acquired it. Never ſay, I have loſt ſuch a thing, for you have nothing but what's borrowed. If any of your Children dye, bewail him not as if he were loſt; but think it enough to ſay, I have reſtored him to him, to whom he belonged. Be chearful, rather than afflicted, when all you have is taken away from you; for then you will be out of all debt.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. IT matters not how the Creditor got the money due to him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he demand nothing of his Debtor. You are not to look on the perſon whom God hath appointed to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33925:83"/>reſume what you ought him; ſtand not to examine whether that perſon have good or bad qualities, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he has any averſion for you; is it not enough for you to be aſſur'd, that being much indebted, your Creditor does not demand any thing further from you?</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. HE is an abſolute Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who acts and appoints things according, or contrary, to his inclination; yet can you not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe that power, but only over the actions which proceed from virtue, for it does not extend to the goods receiv'd from Fortune: for a man to perſiſt obſtinately in a deſire of being maſter thereof, argues him to be in a diſpoſition, in a ſhort time, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their ſlave.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:33925:84"/>
            <p n="54">LIV. TWere a great act of wiſdom, and withal an extraordinary happineſs, if you could put your ſelf into ſuch a poſture as never come to any diſgrace. And yet this is in your power; all you have to do, is to turn the moſt diſaſtrous accidents to your own advantage, and derive good from evil. Let it be your conſtant perſuaſion, that, ſin excepted, there is no evil but has ſomewhat of good lying concealed under its bark.</p>
            <p n="55">LV. I Am confident you would not be rich, conditionally to be withal a ſlave, ſince that of all the goods that can be enjoyed in this world, there's none countervails liberty. Tell me then, which of the two liberties you would rather loſe, that of the body, or that of the mind? You will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. That no doubt the ſlavery of
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:33925:84"/>the heart is a thouſand times worſe, than that of the body. I grant it; but muſt tell you withal, That the true liberty of the heart cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, otherwiſe than by a generous contempt of wealth.</p>
            <p n="56">LVI. REmember you are a man, and rank whatever happens to you, what nature ſoever it be of, amongſt things incident to Humanity. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your ſelf to work your way through a million of diſgraces, and be no more ſtartled when they ſhall happen, than you are when you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on the like in other men. Are you dangerouſly wounded in the hand or arm? Others have been lam'd as well as you, and that accident is at moſt but a diſparagement.</p>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:33925:85"/>
            <p n="57">LVII. BEware of deſiring every thing that you are pleas'd withal; you muſt look on the means as well as the end. There are ſome very pleaſant and delightful places in the world, where no-body dares go, becauſe the way to them is rough and difficult. I would have that which you deſire to be perfectly good; yet if there be a neceſſity, for the obtaining of it, to do any thing that is unhandſome, and that much trouble is to be gone through, it is my advice, that you think no more of it.</p>
            <p n="58">LVIII. TO judge rightly of affliction, you muſt look on it as the principle and beginning of a very great good, and not as an evil. Be not frightned at the appearance of it: the greateſt Gyant is much leſs than a Fly, when he begins to be fram'd in his mothers womb.</p>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:33925:85"/>
            <p n="59">LIX. NEver comply with the ſentiment of the Populace, and meaſure not things according to the common opinion. 'Tis a great miſtake, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that a man is very happy, and well in health, becauſe he is jocund and chearful: nor are you to have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that he is ſick, or in ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, becauſe he is melancholy, and out of humour. There's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ordinary in the uſe of things, than diſguiſe and perſonation. Do we not daily ſee an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of perſons that are dejected and ſad in the midſt of Honours and Wealth, and others who make an open diſcovery of a frolick humour, though they are in extreme neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity?</p>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:33925:86"/>
            <p n="60">LX. BEfore you judge of a thing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the end well. You may ſafely call a thing good, when it is ſuch in its end, though at firſt it ſeems not to be ſo; and reject as an evil thing what is not good in its end, though it has a plauſible beginning. According to this account, you are not much to eſteem all the things of this world, ſince they are ſo near their end. The goods of this life are leſs conſiderable upon the ſcore of their multitude, than upon that of their continuance.</p>
            <p n="61">LXI. GOod, if we ſtrictly conſider it, conſiſts in action; Virtue is a good that has no dependance on For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and ſuch as Envy cannot faſten on it. Endeavour to become maſter of that good; I aſſure you that you may do it: yet ſince no-body can give
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:33925:86"/>you that treaſure, you muſt not envy thoſe that have found it. What kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſoever a man may have receiv'd from Fortune, he is not, upon that ſcore, ever the more happy, and his apparent felicity ſhould not raiſe any jealouſie in your Soul; be inclin'd ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to commiſerate him, and bemoan his being expos'd to the humorous traverſes and inſolence of Fortune.</p>
            <p n="62">LXII. VVHen you ſhall ſee a man extremely rich, and in good plight, beware of accounting him happy; ſay rather out of a ſentiment of compaſſion; Alas! he is not far from his ruine, at leaſt he is menac'd with ſome great misfortune; and if he live long, he muſt force his way through many diſgraces. A man is not the mark of all thoſe troubleſom accidents, when he is in a mean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and has but little about him. I am content there ſhould be ſome
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:33925:87"/>advantage, nay, ſolidity in the goods which may be acquir'd upon earth; yet will it ſtill be truly affirm'd, that they are not to be eſteem'd, ſince they are nothing elſe but the occaſions of all our evils, and the ſource of all our diſgraces.</p>
            <p n="63">LXIII. YOu will never ſlight or envy a man, if inſtead of reflecting on his preſent condition, you ſeriouſly conſider what he ſometime was, or what he may yet be. Is he now very rich? He may be poor. Is he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to one of the higheſt charges in the Kingdom? It may be you will find him ere long amongſt Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in a Priſon: ſlight him not if he be in neceſſity; for you will ſtand in need of his favour, when Fortune ſhall have re-advanc'd him.</p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:33925:87"/>
            <p n="64">LXIV. IF you take it unkindly to be deny'd what might be eaſily granted to a Flatterer, you are no better than he; at leaſt your complaint is not very reaſonable. Are you yet ignorant, that the things of this world are never beſtow'd for nothing, but, on the contrary, that they are alwayes dearly ſold, and that the Coyn that's moſt current amongſt men, is Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery? It you have not proffer'd it to any one, why do you think it much, that you have nothing given you? And if you have made uſe of it as well as others, why do you not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by a ſincere repentance, to cleanſe your ſelf of the fault you have committed?</p>
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:33925:88"/>
            <p n="65">LXV. IN bargaining, one gives, the other receives ſomething; but he who buyes nothing, keeps what he had. Complain not that you are deny'd what is not ordinarily granted but to Crimes. Content your ſelf with what you were poſſeſs'd of before, and think it enough that you are not become wicked. 'Tis no ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to you, that you have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd your ſelf in ſo great a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and that you had been able to ſlight what had only the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of good.</p>
            <p n="66">LXVI. HE muſt be a Fool, who ſells him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to buy a garment; how then dare you deliver up your mind to ſatisfie your body? Whoever is diſquieted for the accommodations and enjoyments of the body, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a ſlave to what he wiſhes. You
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33925:88"/>have but your deſert, when, for having over-pamper'd your Body, your Soul is reduc'd to a ſhameful ſlavery.</p>
            <p n="67">LXVII. THere's nothing more admirable, or more worthy the eſteem of all ſorts of perſons, than a generous Soul that reſolutely rejects applauſe, and is not ſo injurious to that virtue, as to ſerve it upon the ſcore of intereſt or deſign. You cannot find any thing greater among men, than a noble, generous, and tranſcendent mind, which wiſely deſpiſes what moſt others are dazled and charm'd withal. Now thus does he demean himſelf, who ſlights Honour, and cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the incenſe of Flatterers.</p>
            <p n="68">LXVIII. THe goods of this life are like Nettles, which, in their verdure, make a delightful proſpect at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but ſting their hands who
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33925:89"/>touch them. What we deſire, or hope, ſeems perfectly good to us, while it is at a diſtance; but when we have it in our hands, it wounds us to the very heart.</p>
            <p n="69">LXIX. A Fool is always deſiring, and does not ſo much as confider what is within his power, though ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily it be ſomething better than what he pretends to. Thus ſuch perſons enjoy not any thing, while they are deſirous of all. Deſires oppoſe one another, and are in a cruel War, in order to their mutual deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="70">LXX. IT is a hard matter to obtain that which many perſons wiſh; but I conceive it alſo as difficult, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it after it has been obtain'd. The great number of Competitors does many times obſtruct mens com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing their deſigns; but that of the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:33925:89"/>Envious troubles and diſturbs a man in his poſſeſſion. In fine, the more one deſires a thing, the further he is from it.</p>
            <p n="71">LXXI. TAke here in few words, the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a wiſe man, and the exact idea which may be given of him. He ſhould be willing to have a thing, without deſiring it; Fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and be in a continual ſtate of precaution; be contented, and avoid pleaſure; not love any thing but what is conformable to reaſon; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for whatever is neceſſary, and yet never be diſquieted; not take any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement, but what's conſiſtent with decency; not be afflicted, but when he has committed ſome fault; though he ought not to be chargeable with that, ſince he makes it his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to follow reaſon in all things.</p>
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:33925:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="72">LXXII. A Good man has this advantage, that he thinks himſelf happy amidſt the greateſt torments; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he is not deceiv'd. Whatever cannot blemiſh his virtue, he does not account any evil. Sin is the only thing he fears: he conſtantly ſuffers puniſhment, he ſhuns pleaſure; he with a generous contempt ſurveys the extent of Fortune's Territories, and he oppoſes all her power, without any other relief, than what he derives from his own patience and courage.</p>
            <p n="73">LXXIII. BE alwayes vigilant againſt the moſt unwelcome and unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed accidents, and order your ſelf ſo, as that all the misfortunes that can hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, may rather prevent your will, than your judgment. The wiſeſt of all Mortals, do what he can, cannot plead an exemption from the diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:33925:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>and misfortunes of this life; but he has this more than others, that he is never ſurpriz'd. Do not determine any thing, without this additional Clauſe, <hi>If ſome traverſe of Fortune do not hinder me.</hi> It is good not to fear Fortune, but it is good alſo to prevent her; that ſo a man be not the Butt of her humorous counter-changes.</p>
            <p n="74">LXXIV. IF it happen that things prove not ſo ill as you thought they would have done, though the ſucceſs be not fully according to your deſire, yet that little diſgrace will give you ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. When a man does not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe himſelf any ſucceſs, a man is the leſs diſcontented to find himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by his own deſires.</p>
            <p n="75">LXXV. THink rather on what may, than on what ordinarily does hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen; that's the true way to live in
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33925:91"/>much tranquillity. For as men do more chearfully ſupport an evil they have been accuſtom'd to; ſo are they leſs ſurpriz'd at an accident, how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſoever it may be, when by fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight they have prepar'd themſelves for the reception of it. They who take a Voyage, though the weather be fair, and no likelihood of danger at that time, will nevertheleſs provide the ſhip with all things neceſſary to ſave themſelves from a wrack, in caſe a Tempeſt ſhould riſe. Thus ought a prudent man to do; while good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune favours him, he prepares himſelf for the entertainment of the bad.</p>
            <p n="76">LXXVI. SInce 'tis thought a kind of liberty to obey a wiſe man, it muſt alſo be ſaid, that it is a kind of ſervitude to have the government of immodeſt and impudent perſons. A Fool is tormented with two ſtrange evils; the one, that he is a Fool; the other,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:33925:91"/>that he ſupplies the want of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with ill nature. For as a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet man does by his good conduct ſupply whatever elſe is wanting to him; ſo he who wants conduct and diſcretion, pieces out that want with the malignancy of his mind.</p>
            <p n="77">LXXVII. <hi>ARiſtotle</hi> wiſely obſerv'd, That it was the property of Fools to be alwayes judging of all ſorts of things; to determine haſtily without conſulting reaſon, not to make uſe of preſent goods, and never to ſtudy the knowledge of what may make a man happy in this world. I ſhall add to the reflection of that great perſon, that there is no folly like that of a man, who, being not ignorant in what the good and felicity of this life conſiſts, yet leads a very irregular life.</p>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:33925:92"/>
            <p n="78">LXXVIII. PErfect wiſdom does not ſo much conſiſt in diving into the higheſt Sciences, as in framing a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in a man's deſigns, words, and all his enterprizes. 'Tis a great mark of wiſdom, for a man to embrace only that which is good in it ſelf, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of trifling away his time in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the myſteries and ſecrets of Natures; to moderate the impetuous ſallies of the paſſions, inſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fruitleſs ſpeculations, and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd diſcourſes; to ſtudy the art of Self-content, and to defie all depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on Fortune.</p>
            <p n="79">LXXIX. I Account that man happy, who wants fewer things to live quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with pleaſure, than he does, ſimply to live. To live, he ſtands in need of ſuſtenance, rayment, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other things: to live contentedly,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:33925:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſuffices that he have a tranſcendent Soul, which indifferently contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plates good and bad Fortune, which eſteems only that which is to laſt eternally, which does her utmoſt to become like God, and finds her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, joy, and felicity, in the contempt ſhe makes of all the goods dependent on Fortune.</p>
            <p n="80">LXXX. TIs more eaſie than it is imagin'd, for a man to become maſter of all the world; 'tis but to ſlight all, and make an excellent uſe of things, The excellency of a Demesne is to be computed by the profit iſſuing out of it: now it is manifeſt, that no man makes a better uſe of, and derives a greater advantage from, all the things in this world, than he, who, upon the account of virtue, deſpiſes them.</p>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:33925:93"/>
            <p n="81">LXXXI. ALl wicked men are ſlaves, only the virtuous man is perfectly free. Can any one imagine a more abſolute liberty than that which you enjoy, when no-body can hinder you from living as you pleaſe your ſelf? A Libertine is far from being ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as you are, for he is engag'd by an unhappy neceſſity to obey his paſſions, and to ſuffer himſelf to be ſway'd by the moſt infamous Vices. The Laws forbid him to ſeek what he deſires, and he has not the freedom ſo much as to wiſh that which is good, ſince his being reduc'd to a ſlavery to his own lewd inclinations. But nothing can obſtruct his deſires and enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who has embrac'd the party of virtue; he wholly cleaves to that which is of good repute, and alwayes follows reaſon, as the rule of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and comportment.</p>
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:33925:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="82">LXXXII. THere's no liberty like that of a man who is accuſtom'd to will only what God wills; nothing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to him contrary to his will, and he executes all his deſigns, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſtrongeſt oppoſitions. A man is abſolutely maſter of himſelf, when, inſtead of making things vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently comply with his humour, he can accommodate his guſt and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to the things themſelves. Is it not an argument of great liberty, that a man can abſolutely diſpoſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?</p>
            <p n="83">LXXXIII. TIs a vain brag, to ſay, that you are a King; if you be not vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, you are a ſlave: but if you are a good and juſt man, you are truly a King, though engag'd by your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to wait on others. The volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous perſon is not a ſlave to one
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:33925:94"/>man, but to many vices; the virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man has an abſolute juriſdiction over his own heart, and has the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to aſſume the title of King over all his paſſions. What do you call reigning, but to be inveſted with a great power not deriv'd from any other perſon? And where, think you, that is to be found? Ask the famous <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> and he will tell you, that that ſoveraign authority is inveſted in perſons endow'd with perfect wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p n="84">LXXXIV. PAtience has an admirable faculty in retorting injuries, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hinders a man from doing them to any one. If your Soul be ſo rightly byas'd, as not to eſteem any thing in this world but virtue only, you will not be much ſenſible of affronts and injuries, and the moſt diſaſtrous acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents will not ſhake your conſtancy, nor will you look on them any longer
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:33925:94"/>as evils. Never concern your ſelf at another's ſpeaking evil of you; in fine, if you are truly wiſe, you will never be alarm'd, unleſs it be when you ſhall find your ſelf chargeable with ſome fault.</p>
            <p n="85">LXXXV. MAke it not your buſineſs to pleaſe all People, only endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to imitate thoſe who are truly-wiſe, and conſummate in virtue. Do you what is incumbent on you, and let people grumble as they pleaſe. For my part, I think it a great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation not to pleaſe the vicious: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well who they are who approve what you do; it is much better to be pleaſing to one ſingle perſon, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he be virtuous, and knows how to diſcern things aright, than a great number of people corrupted by vice. I have learnt this leſſon of one of the Oracles of Philoſophy, That a good and virtuous man is not abſolutely
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:33925:95"/>happy, if he be not ſlighted by the common ſort of people.</p>
            <p n="86">LXXXVI. ACcuſtom your ſelf to do well upon all occaſions; there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more dearly kept up than eſteem. Of all diſeaſes, there's none ſo hardly curable as that of reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſpecially when it has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready blaſted. Reputation is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd without happineſs; but for the preſervation of it, a man muſt be very expert, and not ſpare any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or care.</p>
            <p n="87">LXXXVII. A Virtuous man may be innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reveng'd of his enemies, by perſiſting in well-doing, and a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, by reforming his life. O happy revenge! ſince it is of very great advantage to the one, and does not hurt the others.</p>
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:33925:95"/>
            <p n="88">LXXXVIII. IF what is ſaid of you be conſonant to Truth, entertain it as an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement of great importance. If it be a falſhood, never be troubled at it, and aſſure your ſelf, that Calumny will but augment your Reputation. It will alwayes be a glory to you, that your enemy was forc'd to make uſe of detraction and impoſture, as having not found any thing he could juſtly blame in your demeanour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</p>
            <p n="89">LXXXIX. SIde not with your enemy, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king too much to heart the things he publiſhes againſt you; for he ſayes them only to make you angry; and it is not his deſign to make you a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter man, by diſcovering his animoſity againſt you; but all his pretence is only to moleſt and diſturb you. Be therefore reveng'd of him, ſince it is
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:33925:96"/>in your power to do ſo; and to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate him of his expectation, correct your own miſcarriages, be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd at him, and ſlight his inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p n="90">XC. WHen you ſee things are paſt all remedy, endeavour as to your part to redreſs them as much as you can, in moderating your diſcontent by the contempt of the very thing which occaſion'd it, or by a ſerious reflection on the damage which may attend a violent affliction. If the evil be remedileſs, beware of deſpair: the malice of men may reduce us to very great extremities, out of which there may be no hopes of recovery; but 'tis we our ſelves only are capable of depriving our paſſions of the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which are proper for them.</p>
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:33925:96"/>
            <p n="91">XCI. ANger does it ſelf more hurt than is imagin'd, for it deprives it ſelf of reaſon and ſound apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when it ſtands in greateſt need of them. You will grant me, that there is a neceſſity of much penetration and judgment, to get ones ſelf out of a great danger, as well as to be exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Folly: tell me then, I pray, whether we can poſſibly conceive a greater danger, or a more remarkable extravagance, than for a man to run the hazard of loſing his life, to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his revenge.</p>
            <p n="92">XCII. WHen you have troubled and turmoyl'd your ſelf long to pitch upon a time fit for revenge, and yet meet with great obſtacles to your deſign, what have you gain'd but much diſcontent, exaſperation, and deſpight? It may be further added,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:33925:97"/>that you have given your enemy a fair occaſion to be reveng'd of you; ſo that the ſame thing becomes your puniſhment, and your revenge.</p>
            <p n="93">XCIII. ARe you reduc'd to Poverty? You ought to take comfort, becauſe you ſhall live in ſafety; whereas they who are Rich, have alwayes occaſion to tremble, finding themſelves expos'd to a thouſand dreadful occurrences. 'Twas well enough that you had the one in exchange for the other; but your lot is yet the better, ſince Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the other miſeries and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of this life, ſignifie almoſt nothing, in compariſon of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtrous misfortunes which perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threaten the Rich.</p>
            <p n="94">XCIV. RId your ſelf as ſoon as you can of thoſe kinds of things, which being preſerv'd with too much ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:33925:97"/>are as if they were loſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gold is like a malignant humour, that ſhould be ſuddenly dry'd up and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd, to prevent approaching death. They are guilty of a ſtrange unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in point of ſtewardſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, who do not employ their ſuperfluous goods in the relief of the poor and miſerable. Know, that what is ſuperfluous belongs to them, and that God has not entruſted you with it, but to relieve them in their exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p n="95">XCV. I Know not whether there be any Folly equal to that of a man, who, deſirous to eſtabliſh himſelf in a perfect independency, and not to be ſubject to any-body, thinks it the right way to attain that end, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſlave to wealth. One man may, without any infamy, obey ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man; but it muſt ever be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious, for a man to be a Captive to a metal.</p>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:33925:98"/>
            <p n="96">XCVI. AMbitious men, who would have a ſovereignty over others, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mind that they are ſlaves to their own paſſions, and that they obey I know not how many Vices. Whoever thinks to relie on Fortune, will not go very far under ſo weak a protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it would be more honourable, and more for his advantage, to take Virtue for his Conductreſs. A virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man cannot avoid being a happy man; and he will alwayes be in great authority, while he keeps an abſolute ſupremacy over his heart and his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p n="97">XCVII. A Man ought not to fear the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfulneſs and inſolence of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, when he is but in a mean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. 'Tis better for him not to be expos'd to ſo many dangers, than to have much ſuperfluity. We could
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:33925:98"/>inſtance in abundance of perſons, who receive exceſſive favours from For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; and yet, how profuſe ſoever ſhe may be, it is not in her power to ſatisfie a man who deſires more than is requiſite. He who will miſ-ſpend his money, has not any in bank. 'Tis a vaſt charge to nurſe up, and keep a Vice.</p>
            <p n="98">XCVIII. YOu vainly flatter your ſelf with the conceit of being a virtuous man, meerly becauſe you have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd contempt. You have at moſt but equalled your patience to that of an ambitious perſon, who makes no difficulty to overcome a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand diſgraces to compaſs his end. Do you expect to be commended, becauſe your Virtue is very much like the Vice of another? Alas! what meanneſs of ſpirit muſt it needs ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue in a man, not to be willing to endure more, in order to the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:33925:99"/>of an eternal reward, than the followers of the world for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of Honours and Tranſitory Goods?</p>
            <p n="99">XCIX. IT is much better not to be ſubject to Diſcontent, than to receive much Conſolation. All the joyes in the world cannot take one grey hair out of our heads; but there needs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome diſturbances of mind, and a little melancholy, to make us hoary before our time. That man muſt have a great ſtock of recollection and wiſdom, who is never troubled at any thing, and can live contentedly in a general privation of thoſe pleaſures and enjoyments, which moſt people do over-earneſtly covet.</p>
            <p n="100">C. MEn complain and repine in bad Fortune, and they are inſolent and inſupportable in good Fortune.
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:33925:99"/>There's, no condition but is ſubject to ſome Vice, ſave only that which imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates Virtue, keeping conſtantly the middle, and carefully declining from all the extremes. You ſee then, that it is not ſo difficult, as is commonly imagin'd, to acquire Virtue; all that a man has to do, is to ſupport bad Fortune without Repining, and to live in Proſperity without Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
